<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply unto a pamphlet entituled an ansvver to certain certificates, serving to vindicate Mr. Samuel Eaton's righteousness in receiving tvvo summes of money, &amp;c. Wherein the soulness, falseness, and scandalousnes of that answer is made to apear by the elders, deacons, and many of the members of the church of Christ, commonly called the church of Duckenfield meeting in Stopport.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91671</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896473</idno>
  <idno type="VID">154339</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240920158</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1083A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896473</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99896473e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2412:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply unto a pamphlet entituled an ansvver to certain certificates, serving to vindicate Mr. Samuel Eaton's righteousness in receiving tvvo summes of money, &amp;c. Wherein the soulness, falseness, and scandalousnes of that answer is made to apear by the elders, deacons, and many of the members of the church of Christ, commonly called the church of Duckenfield meeting in Stopport.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2412 lacks pages 21-24.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Money --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154339:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY UNTO A PAMPHLET ENTITULED An Ansvver to certain Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, serving to vindicate Mr. <hi>Samuel Eaton</hi>'s righteousness in receiving tvvo summes of money, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The foulness, falseness, and scandalousnes of that answer is made to apear by the <hi>Elders, Deacons,</hi> and many of the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of</hi> CHRIST, commonly called <hi>The Church of Duckenfield mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in</hi> Stopport.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:154339:2"/>
            <head>A Prefatorie <hi>EPISTLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHrist saith to his Disciples, That it is impossible but that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences will come, but he denounceth a woe to them through whom they come whom they come; and the reason is, because by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences much Dishonour comes to God, much Reproach to the Gospel, much Shame to Gods People, and much bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to Gods Adversaries; growth in piety is obstructed, the way of God is evil spoken of, many are made weak, and many fall. It ought not therefore to appear strange, that there are offences among us: As from God it is a most righteous thing that it should be so; we have been a people of many mercies and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but have not walked so humbly, self-denyingly, so holily with our God as we ought to have done: and it cannot be thought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, but that Satan will envy our liberties, and will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to stirre up adversaries against us: and it hath heen the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Churches of Christ, that from among themselves some have risen to speak perverse things: and if it be our condition that some that were of us have lifted up their heel against us, and by false and slanderous imputations against us have attempted to render us odious, and to make base and contemptible the works and service of Christ in our hands, it is a thing not to be wondered at, onely it is to be lamented, that those that are enemies to all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion should have such an advantage given to them to laugh it to scorn in us. The scandall indeed is very high and great at this time, by something which God hath suffered to fall out among us; and it is to be feared that some may stumble at the way of truth, by reason of it; but woe to them by whom the stumbling-block is laid, unlesse they repent. Endeavours are not wanting to make us the faulty persons, while we have been onely exercising that power of Christ among us, upon persons whom we have judged to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per subjects thereof; and we stand upon our defence against those that shall accuse us, that we have not erred for substance by male-administration; and we are willing it stould be brought to the test. But be it that we have acted like men, like weak men, and have been mistaken in the application of that great Ordinance of Christ to the subject, we have cause to be humbled upon that account; yet will not our weaknesse be any excuse to their wickednesse, who have acted against us; for they have risen up against, and with a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant
<pb facs="tcp:154339:2"/> spirit have opposed a due and just power, as to them, though unduly put forth by us, as they would have it, in that act of censure against them. Now this is altogether unjustifiable and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in reference to any power, whether Ecclesiastiall or Politicall, whether exercised in Church or Common-wealth, and tends to the subversion of all power and of all order among men, and will be the root of all confusion in all societies of men. And whether the power which we exercise be lawfull in it self, simply considered, though it may fall under debate, and may be thought worthy of dispute, yet it must be granted without dispute, that when a power is acknowledged to be the power of Chaist, and when persons have made choice of it, and have set it up, and have put themselves under it, and have made such persons their Rulers, and Governours, and Iudges, to determine of them and of their affaires, they ought then to submit and yield up themselves to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to be contented to stand or fall as they determine; yea though it should come to passe (as it will sometimes be, while fraile men have the management of affaires) that they should misse it in their administrations; yet such persons (though they may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest what sense they have of that wrong, if it be wisely and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly done) may not violently oppose themselves against that power, much lesse revile and vilifie with all opprobrious language the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that have acted in it, as these persons have done some of us, whom themselves made choice of in the beginning, rejoicing greatly that they could be under a power that suited their own principles.</p>
            <p>Let it therefore be seriously considered what temptations these persons are under who do thus rebell against their own power, which is therefore theirs (as themselves would sometimes have said) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they judge it to be Christs, which should be a bond upon their conscience to submission. Are they to be heeded or regarded in their judging of us who are their judges? especially while they vent themselves in revengefull exclamations against us without proof? We would desire that our Brethren of the Presbyterian judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be circumspect what countenance they give them, what credit they bestow upon them, what friendship they afford them, what admittance they grant them into their company, though but onely in a civil way, lest they harden them in their sin: discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented members cut off, if they may be heard and heartned against those that proceed against them, will without question tell a faire tale for themselves, and load their censurers with calumnies. But
<pb facs="tcp:154339:3"/> the credit of a society of professing Saints, which desire to keep a good conscience in all things should sway more with wise and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous souls then two or three distempered and enraged spirits. We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould wish that in this our brethren would do unto us as they would expect that it should be done to them in the like case; we do professe that there would be a religious tie upon us to abstain from all kind of fellowship with their excommunicate members, till the matter might be brought to a faire hearing: and we desire the same from them, and we would make the same request unto all others into whose hands that shameful Pamplet, printed and subscribed by three of them, hath or may come, that they would be cautious what they receive or entertain especially if it reflect upon others; for this we do assert, that we have not seen at any time such a bundle of untruths &amp; slanders packed up together in so little room. We are the persons that their discourse is directed to, though some of us be more pointed at than others, and Mr <hi>Eaton</hi> is struck at in all. We therefore are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to appear in the reply to it: and because we are not all of us alike able to speak to all things that are unduly and untruly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon one or other of us by these persons; and because many others of the society to which we appertaine can speak as punctually to many things as we our selves can, &amp; in some things more exactly &amp; perfectly therefore they and we have affixed our names to many of the principal things in their Pamphlet, putting them into the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin over against the place such things are mentioned in: and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our witnesses are so many, that we are forced to pretermit the particular nomination of all, lest we should be too tedious to the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ader: And we do not make use of women to give witnesse to any thing, though there be many among us who know the truth of those things we assert, because we need t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; and many things are so clear in themselves, and so undeniable, that they require not the testimony of any, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore none are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought. We would intreat this favour, that all that have read and heard of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir scand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lous Paper which they have published, especially if it have left any impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssion on their minds, would be pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to take so much p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins, as with seriousn sse to read this Reply, that the judgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt they make may be made according to righteousnesse, and not as persons shall fancy either one or other. This is the whole of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Barret</hi> Elder.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Partington</hi> Elder.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Thomson</hi> Elder.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Linney</hi> Elder.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Tipping</hi> Deacon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thoma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Newton</hi> Deacon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Johnson</hi> Deacon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Wharmby</hi> Deacon.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154339:3"/>
            <head>A REPLY To a false and scandalous PAMPHLET, Entituled An Answer to certain Certificates Printed for clearing of Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> from unjust charges laid upon him, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The answer of <hi>Robert Ridgway</hi> and <hi>Iohn Bruckshaw.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur desires are not to cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersions upon the persons of others, but to clear the truth and our selves from those aspersions of lying, forging, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154339:4"/> Calumniators, &amp;c. endeavoured to be cast upon us by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid Certificates; for our resolves were to sit down in silence, as to Printing, had we not by the said Certificates been constrained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Yet we are assured that some of the persons whose names are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto subscribed, and in particular <hi>Colonel Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables,</hi> was ignorant of printing thereof, until they came to publick view. We shall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the first place shew the ground and the rise of the whole matter, which was as followeth.</p>
               <p>At the Assises held at <hi>Chester, October 6. 1656.</hi> We lying at <hi>Ralph Halls</hi> house, who and his wife are Members of Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Church, his wife gave us a relation of something that troubled her, about forty shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings given them by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154339:4"/>
                  <hi>Colonel Venables,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> said was but lent them, to be repayed by the Church; and that the greatest burthen of it must lie upon him: which rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at the request and importunity of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Barret</hi> (one of the Elders) whose hand is at the foresaid Cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, to whom she also told it, we gave in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting under our hands to the Church, being produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the aforesaid <hi>William Barret,</hi> as witnesses of what we heard, according as we have herein hereafter declared.</p>
               <p>Unto which relation so given unto us, I <hi>John Bruckshaw</hi> replyed, as you are a sister, <hi>&amp; Ralph</hi> a Brother, and I know nothing against you, I dare not but belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you; yet this I must say, the thing is so odious, and looketh with such a black face, that I must
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154339:5"/> think, that unless a man were out of his senses he should not so say. Witness my hand,</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Bruckshaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>and <hi>Robert Ridgway.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154339:3"/>
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>The Authors of this Pamphlet would have the World to believe that their act in Printing was an act of necessity,<note place="margin">Themselves confess this.</note> and that their desires were not to cast aspersions upon others: but if so, why did they take up a report from <hi>Ralph Halls</hi> wife? which reflected upon Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> (an Elder, and their teaching Officer) as if he had told a lie, and as if he had been unrighteous in a summe of money received by him: And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154339:4"/> why did they carry that report a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and divulge it in places where they came, so that many within the Church to which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> relates, and many also that appertain not unto it, had the knowledge thereof to the wounding of Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, before ever he had heard any thing thereof,<note place="margin">Tho. Partington Will. Thomson. Will. Linney. Rob. Warmsham Tho. Newton. Iohn Warmbee. Peter Fernhead. Tho. Gellibrand James Walker. and the other forenamed, and many other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides.</note> as by his grief up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hearing of it did appear to us? And why did they not first acquaint him with it, and satisfie themselves concerning the truth of it before they had published it? Yea, why did they make additions to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they had from her? which rendred the matter more vile and foul, then all that she presented to them, as will hereafter appear.</p>
                  <p>And was it not high time to print Certificates, when the report of Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> unrighteousness was so far disperst abroad in these parts, that one could scarce go any whither, but he might meet with it, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of it read in publick assemblies?</p>
                  <p>And what if some of them (or all) whose hands are at the Certificates, were ignorant of the Printing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? were any ignorant of the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates themselves? did not all certify as are mentioned in the printed papers? And did they not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certifie, that others might know how unjustly Mr. <hi>Ea.</hi> had suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under such reports whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h were of him, and with a designe to wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the reproch that lay upon him?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154339:4"/> And was not Printing (the slander having been made so publick) the most likely expedient to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish that end?</p>
                  <p>As for the relation which these persons have made concerning the discourse betwixt themselves and <hi>Ralph Halls</hi> wife, it is partial and deceitful, it doth not contain the whole, nor the principal part of what she spake, and of what they repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; yea, it is not a true relation, for it containeth not any part of the discourse betwixt <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi> and them,<note place="margin">See the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> which the Certificate doth point at, as they themselves very well know; for they have in it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented something that hath the face of a lie, but not any thing of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, which is the onely thing the Certificates m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke mention of: yet because they have produced this to the view of the world, with design (as may well be thought) of casting further filth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> then onely of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, there shall be a true an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer returned to it.</p>
                  <p>Let it be granted that <hi>Colonel Venables</hi> gave that forty shillings to <hi>Ralph Hall,</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> said it was but lent, and must be repayed by the Church, yet there is no lie in this, for thus it was; Mrs. <hi>Venables</hi> intreated Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> to procure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shillings from the Church for <hi>Ralph Hall,</hi> and urged him with this Argument, that he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154339:5"/> forty shillings from <hi>Colonel Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables,</hi> and it was lent, and must be repaid; whence Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it was lent to him, and must be repayed by him, or by the Church for him. And Mrs. <hi>Venables</hi> did not clear it up at that time, how or by whom it was lent, or how or by whom it must be repayed, nor afterwards, till Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> came to be defamed about it, and then she declared how it was, and cleared him from a lie in it by a Letter under her own hand.</p>
                  <p>This business cost the Elders (some of them) a journey to <hi>Chester</hi> to search out the truth,<note place="margin">William Barret. Willi. Thomson</note> and they found it to be a mistake, into which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was in a sort unavoydably led by Mrs. <hi>Venables</hi> her dark and defective expressions.</p>
                  <p>But this is not to the purpose in hand; there is another part of <hi>Ioyce Halls</hi> relation, which is wholly supprest in the account they have given. Their report (as from her) was this, that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Venables</hi> had told her, that he had formerly sent to the Church from <hi>Ireland</hi> such a summe of money, and did ask her whether she had her share in it, and that she answered no, she had not so much as heard of it; and that thereupon Mrs. <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> said to her husband, sure you sent it to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> did you not?<note place="margin">William Barret. Tho. Partington. Willi. Thomson. Joh. Wharmbee. Wil. Linnie. Edward Hall. Rob. Warming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham. Tho. Gillebrand John Harrison. John Wharmbee. Jam. Walker. Joh. Sidebottom Tho. Goodier. Joh. Warburton.</note> and that he replyed no, not to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> but to the Church, and that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> knowes well enough, for I sent him other monyes. In these last expressions lies the gross lie and forgerie which the Certificate speaks of; for Colonel <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> professeth that he never uttered any such word, and that the thing it self (<hi>viz.</hi> of sending other monies) was altogether false; and <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi> denies that ever she made any such rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> persons: and upon examination, it did appear to us (she and they being brought together) that it was framed out of their own brain: but take it as themselves present it, if the thing were so odious, that unless a man were out of his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, it could not be thought that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> would say it, why then was it blazed abroad to render him odious, they not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving spoken unto him any thing of the matter? it was but one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154339:5"/> person, and that a Sister (as she is called) that did assert it as from Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> unto them; and the Scripture saith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not an Accusation against an Elder under two or three witnesses, much less divulge it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154339:5"/>
               <head>Answer to the Certificate.</head>
               <p>We say first, none of the persons you intend in your Certificates did ever mention <hi>28 l.</hi> then who are the liars? Is it not as great a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake in you to put <hi>28 l.</hi> for <hi>26. l.</hi> as for <hi>Ioice Hall</hi> to put <hi>26 l.</hi> for <hi>24 l.?</hi> Secondly, we ask, whether it be a grosse lie forged by persons of distemper'd spirits, to testifie what we were informed of by <hi>Ioice Hall,</hi> and that when we were requested thereunto by <hi>William Barret?</hi> which we did give in under our hands, being called thereunto as witnesses, and not as a positive charge against Mr <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> And your selves have said, two Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives will carry it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154339:6"/>
                  <hi>500</hi> Negatives; then why not our two Affirmatives against her Negative? And <hi>William Barret</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid told <hi>George Downes</hi> (one of your Members) that <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> cleared us; and <hi>Katharine Aston,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of your members, likewise saith, <hi>J. Hall</hi> confesseth so much as to clear us. And is it not more like to forgery, to put another mans name to a Letter or Writing without his consent or knowledge, as some of you have done by <hi>John Dand,</hi> as himself openly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>But to come to the Certificate it self; they say none of the persons we intended in it did ever mention the 28 l. But we assert, that menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was made of both the summes, but with uncertainty whether 26 l. or 28 l. as will be proved by wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses.<note place="margin">Will. Barret.</note> But it was never said by any of us, that they were liars upon that account, (that is language more fit for their foul mouths) for that might be onely by a mistake.</p>
                  <p>And it is but a subtil evasion to propose it in form of a Question, whether it be a grosse lie forged by persons of a distempered spirit, to testifie what they were informed of;<note place="margin">The persons that witnessed to the last, are witnesses to this also.</note> for they very well knew that it was not charged upon them for lying, because they related what they were informed of, but because they had reported what they were not informed of; for to say that Col. <hi>Venables</hi> had sent other moneys to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> to cut him off from claiming any part of the 24 l. he sent to the Deacons, was a grosse lie forged by persons of a distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered spirit; for Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> himself (as hath already been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented) denied it, and <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi> gain-said it. And notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154339:6"/> what they speak of <hi>William Barret</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Will. Barret.</note> and <hi>Katharine Ashton,</hi> as witnesses, that <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi> hath clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, (which will not prove so to be, but the contrary) yet they know that <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi> did deny it to their faces, in the presence of the Church, when that businesse was examined, and their allegation of the strength which we our selves have acknowledged to be in two affirmative witnesses above many negative witnesses, will not serve their turn nor stand them in stead; for they had been the divulgers of a slander, and consequently the slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, till they could find an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and upon that account, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had reported such a thing abroad (though in the report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it they might mention <hi>Ioyce Hall</hi>) they were sent unto to come unto the Church, and <hi>William Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> undertook to speak to them; and when they came, the Church looked upon them as Accusers of <hi>Ioyce Hall,</hi> rather than witnesses, till she came to speak for her self; and much more when she was come (together with them) and with high appeals to God (as they know) gain-said them. And her husband also came in (being an ear-witness of the first relation she made unto them at <hi>Chester</hi>) and declated that his wife spake no such thing of Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> his sending other money but that they themselves imagined such a thing,<note place="margin">The same wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses as in the fourth page at bottom.</note> and spake their imagination, and that his wife opposed them therein, and told them Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> did not declare so much to her; yet they notwithstanding did afterwards boldly repo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t what they themselves had devised: Might it not then be said in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154339:6"/> Certificate, that it was a grosse lie forged by persons of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempered spirit? let intelligent men judge. What relates to <hi>Iohn Dand</hi> must receive this answer; It is not known who put his name to the Letter, nor acknowledged that it was put unto it without his knowledge, though he doth not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it; for <hi>Iohn Dand</hi> himself confesseth that he was spoken unto about the businesse, and gave answer to the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Letter, suitably to those that subscribed the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, upon which account he conceives his name was affixed to it with the rest of the persons whose names are in it: a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of his own writing declares so much, which is with us.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154339:6"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed that the <hi>24 l.</hi> was sent unto the Church, and not unto him, &amp; that he wrote to Colonell <hi>Venables,</hi> that his contributions were small, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the Letter from Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> you mention. We quere then if Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> changed his mind, first, who was the Author? secondly, what ground had he for such a change? thirdly, what he had to do with that he had before given? <hi>Act. 5.4.</hi> And if not so sent at first, why did
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154339:7"/> Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> say so? where lies the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>It is Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi>'s portion which the Lord at this time hath measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out unto him, to lie under the scourge of bold, yet false Accusers: We were present, and very many more besides us (for it was at a Church-meeting it seemes) that these words should be spoken (as was confessed at <hi>Northwich</hi>) and we professe that we remember not that any such thing was spoken by Mr. <hi>Eaton;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">William Linnie. Tho. Partington. Tho. Newton. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>earnhead. Tho. Gellebrand Rob. Warming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham. James Walker. Joh. Sydebottom Tho. Siddall. John Brombell.</note> and it is so remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a thing, that we know not how we should all of us forget it, if such a thing had been; for Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> voice is audible enough, that all might hear that were present, and some of us more easily than <hi>Robert Ridgeway,</hi> who is the onely person that asserts it against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and sate at further distance from him that day than many of us did. And Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> himself protests against it as a notorious untruth; and Colonell <hi>Venables,</hi> to whom this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154339:7"/> Letter should he written,<note place="margin">Th. Partington. Joh. Sydebottom</note> said, he knew nothing of the matter, or words to that purpose: so far is he from acknowledging that he changed his mind about it. And the Letter that is extant and owned by him contradicts it; for it speaks of no money sent, but of some that was owing to Mr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was intreated to get him; and Col. <hi>Venables</hi> upon the receit would pay so much to Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> there; and when gotten, it was to supply the defect of his contribution in the time of his absence, and then it could not possibly be to the use of the Church, excluding Mr <hi>Eaton;</hi> the Queries then which they make are causelesse, foolish and frivolous, wanting a foundation. If Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> wrote no such Letter, and if there was no such change in Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> what Author then could there be of it? what ground could there be for it? what transgression could there be in it against <hi>Acts</hi> 5.4? Thus they trouble the Reader with their sense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse fictions. This was charged at <hi>Northwich</hi> before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, but they fell in it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> said further, if he might not take it upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he might upon this, <hi>viz.</hi> because Mrs. <hi>Venables,</hi> the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels first wife, whilest she lived, gave <hi>2 s. 6 d.</hi> a day, which upon computation would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to <hi>20 l.</hi> since she died: but how justly he might so take it, let
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154339:7"/> others judge, who if they will take the pains Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> did, may know how long Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> paid for a dead wife.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>They are fruitfull in invention, and do find out new things to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> with, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor we heard of before, but as abusive to him as any thing hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, &amp; as little suitable to truth, but very suitable to that evil spirit of wresting and perverting the most candid expressions, which have come both upon him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wherewith of long time they did disturb the peace of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> (that time which they intend) called us together, that he might clear himself from such
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154339:7"/> scandal as was upon him through them, in reference to that money;<note place="margin">Will. Barret. Tho. Partington. William Linnie. Tho. Newton. Peter Fernhead. Tho. Gillebrand Rob. Warming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham. Jam. Walker. Joh. Sidebottom</note> he spake nothing of taking it upon one account or other, but told us that the Deacons had disposed such a sum of money to him, and that it was no more in proportion then what was due unto him, because Mr. <hi>Venables</hi> when present did contribute two shillings six pence each Sabbath, and in his absence his wife at that time did it; and since her death it hath been neglected, and Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> in that summe which he sent at that time, had onely supplied that defect;<note place="margin">William Barret. Tho Partington. William Linnie. Willi. Thomson Edw. Tipping. Iohn Warmbee. Tho Newton. Edward Hall. Ralph Dickenson Joh. Sidebottom Pet. Fernehead. and all other members of the Church.</note> for if it were computed, it would arise to such a summe. This we know to be true, for Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> was, and is a member of our Congregation as well as she was, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the Rules according to which we walked in those times, and knew (as these persons do, at le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st one of them) and were not ashamed to own them and with joy to walk in them, though they now expose them to the scorn of the world, that the burthen in maintaining Officers and relieving persons in necessity, was born by a joynt shoulder: And whether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent or absent relation did oblige unto it, if there were abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And thence it was that having been long absent, he orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red four and twenty pounds to be given, to supply the defect of his contribution in the time of his absence, therein mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festing what sense was upon him of a duty to be performed by him, so that those words, who ever will take the pains Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> did, may know how long Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> paid for a dead wife; are but a scornful, unjust and unchristian scoffe and jeer, for which, without repentance they are like to give an account. It is dreadful to be considered of, when persons turn persecutors of that way which so lately they owned and rejoyced in as the way of righteousness.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>If Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> did not send other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154339:8"/> to cut him off from having a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y share or part of the twenty four pound, he presented him in a more gentile way with furrs of a good value in England, which were seen by some persons that will attest it at <hi>Harden.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>And if Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> did not send other monies to cut Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154339:8"/> off from having any share in the twenty four pound, as they are now forced to confess, then the greater was their guilt in forging and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, in reporting and publishing so great an untruth,<note place="margin">Will. Barret. Tho. Partington Will. Linney. Will. Thomson. Edw. Tipping. Joh. Wharmbee. Tho. Newton. James Johnson. Edward Hall. Ra. Dickison. Joh. Sydebottom Pet. Fearnhead. Tho. Hughs. Edw. Bradban. &amp;c.</note> and the more have they abused his innocency; And why then do they quarrel at the Certificate that mentions it? and then also Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had undoubted right to the greatest part of it, though he had never been mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As for the furrs of value spoken of as a gentile present, what time they came they were kindly accepted of; but had it been foreseen that he should have been upbraided with them so ungentilely, they would have been rejected with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain; they were some Fox skins undressed, too long kept at <hi>Chester</hi> before he had them, and moths were got into them, and to prevent annoyance and further damage that might be sustained by their hanging within the house, they were carried to the Kilne, where they continued a time, and at last were cast out to the dunghil, as some persons that are now at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> can attest. Nor doth this story of Furrs help at all against the guilt of the lie about other money, because Furrs are not money, and because Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> neither made mention of the one or of the other in this discourse with <hi>Ioyce Hall;</hi> neither did she in her relation to them, nor either of them in their relation to us. All that were at that Church-meeting when the slander was enquired into, do witness the truth of this; nor was this these persons subterfuge, at that time when questioned by the Church, though now they would shelter themselves under it, that the nakedness of that gross lie and forgery they were guilty of might not appear.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>And whereas the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders say, they are bound
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154339:8"/> to clear <hi>Mr.</hi> Eaton, we ask <hi>VVilliam Barret</hi> whether Master <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath cleared himself by bringing the money back to the Church, &amp;c. for he told us that he would never be cleared till he had so done, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You say the money was sent unto the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons dispose; but Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> saith in his Certificate he sent it to the Church; but if it was sent to the Deacons, why were they not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>And because they demand of <hi>William Barret</hi> things reflecting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154339:8"/> reflecting upon Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> greatly to his dishonour, and because we are assured that <hi>William Barret</hi> hath been satisfied all along of Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> integrity and innocency from the time that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> knew what scandalous reports were against him, and had liberty to clear himself from them, (which was done pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely at a Church meeting;) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause what he spake was before that time, and was in private conference with them, and what truth or false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may be therein we understand not; therefore we leave him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn his own answer, which may be at the end of this Paper.</p>
                  <p>And if Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> say in his Certificate that he sent it to the Church, yet he makes mention of a Letter which he authorised Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> to write in his name long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Certificate, in which Letter is the first mention of the twenty four pound, and in it he committeth the money whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the dispose of the Deacons; and this they know well enough, having heard the Letter read, but they have a mind to calumniate, therefore they conceal that part of the Letter which would clear the business, and they express themselves with an (if) when they speak of Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> his sending of it to the Deacons, as if it were uncertain: and they demand, if sent to the Deacons, why were not they acquainted with it? they are willing the Reader should conceive they were not acquainted with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; which yet is a monstruous untruth,<note place="margin">Edw. Tipping. Tho. Newton. Joh. Wharmbee.</note> for three of them not onely knew of the money, but concurred in the dispose of it; and though the fourth remember it not, yet it is probable he was not ignorant of it, nor dissenting from it. For it is likely Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and the other Deacons would tell
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154339:9"/> him of it; or if there were any oversight, yet his brother in law, <hi>Laurence Owen,</hi> who received it, would declare it to him, for it was not made a secret. However it was, yet since it came to be questioned he hath declared to the equity of such proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the money, and hath signified that either he knew and concurred with the others therein, or if he concurred not, it was because he knew it not.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154339:9"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>You say he took it not, but it was ordered for him by the Deacons; your so often mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Deacons comes neerer to lying and forgery, which you would charge upon us, for none of the Deacons we believe knew of it, but <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> who acted more for M. <hi>Eaton</hi> than he did for the Church; as appears by the Elders certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, who say Mr <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> had but twenty pound of the twenty four pound; for when the mony came into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate about <hi>Novemb.</hi> all the Deacons said (except <hi>Th. Newton</hi>) they never heard nor knew of the money.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154339:9"/> Let the Deacons speak themselves one by one, and not in so dark ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions (as by us, or some of us) When was this money ordered to Mr. <hi>Eaton?</hi> was it in <hi>1651?</hi> and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you privy to it but <hi>Thomas Newton?</hi> you formerly denied it, and said, sure <hi>Lawr. Owen</hi> gave it unto him. But why was this word <hi>(But)</hi> put in, to make the Reader think that twenty pound was too little for Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and four pound too much for the poor, or to manifest your sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, slavery, and want of charity? and if four pound was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for the poore, three of that was put into Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> hand, as both he and <hi>Thom. Newton</hi> confessed, but it is not yet known what poor had it, nor what became if the other <hi>20.</hi> shillings.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154339:10"/>
               <p>Again, you say it was by speciall directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a Letter from Mr <hi>Taylor</hi> in <hi>Colonel Venables</hi> name; but none of the Deacons knew of that Letter except <hi>Thomas New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> before Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had the twenty pound, for they knew not of the money, how could they then know of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Letter in his own custody, both from them and the Church, imports that Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> knew Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> directions were not that he should have <hi>20. l.</hi> and the poor but four pound, or that the Church would not be so uncharitable as to make so unequal a division, which though we do not call it Church-robbing, yet was it not a covetous interposing betwixt the poor and the money? Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> directions had been answered, if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154339:11"/> if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had had the better half, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how many persons were to be relieved out of it; for how many of your Members then were and are poor and in debt? we leave them to judge that know them; whose conditions should have been first considered by Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi> direction, by which Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity appeared, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not the money should have been so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. If the power of disposing be in the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, sure it was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture, and then the poor should have had it; for where find you that the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons take care of the Church-Officers?</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>And we do say, that Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> took it not, but that it was ordered he should have it by the Deacons; but these persons, while they do withstand it, do shew a lordly and masterfull spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, wherein little of the fear of God or reverence of men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears; for without respect had to Place, Office, Parts, Worth of any kind, they do with uncivil language entertain one another as if underlings to them. They are offended because the word <hi>Deacons</hi> is so often, though most righteously &amp; necessarily used for the clearing of Mr. <hi>Eaton;</hi> they would make us to be guilty of forgery, because they believe things to be so and so, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they prove it; they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of us things that concern them not, as though they were set over us to take an account from us, being (indeed) Busie-bodies in other mens matters. They condemn, censure, and scandalize us, for things of which they inquire of us how they be.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154339:9"/> They revile us and vilifie us, charging simplicity, slavery, and want of charity upon us, because we have done our duty. They have evill surmisings in their hearts against us, and thereby would beget an evil opinion in the breasts of others against us, because we have not given an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to them how we have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of the money; a thing that we never did, that was never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from us by any particular person, one or other, unlesse the Church call us to it. It was once otherwise with them, or at least one of them; but an evil spirit hath now possessed them.</p>
                  <p>But to answer them what they charge upon us; they say they believe that none of the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons knew of the money but <hi>Thomas Newton.</hi> We say they believe a falsity therein:<note place="margin">Tho. Newton Edw. Tipping. Joh. Wharmbie Deacons. Will. Linney. Tho. Partington R. Warmingsham Joh. Sydebottom James Walker. James Bradbury</note> they say the other Deacons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, they never heard or knew of the money; we say it is falsely and impudently spoken, and we and many others are witnesses against them: They would have us to speak one by one, and not in dark expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions as (by us, and some of us) and they call upon us to speak punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when this money was given to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and whether in 1651. They might do well to take their seats and places, and we will come before them, and submit to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154339:10"/> However, if they be high and lofty, we are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at this time to be lowly, and doe declare particularly, that we three, <hi>Edward Tipping, Thomas Newton,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Wharmby,</hi> in the latter end of 1651. disposed twenty pound of the twenty four pound to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and we divided with much uprightness of heart, without partiality, betwixt him and others which might be in want, according to the utmost of our understanding; in reference unto him we looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a businesse of righteousnesse, that he should have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable maintenance upon the account of his labours amongst us, and that in the first place he should be provided for (for debts must first be paid) and after that all that could be spared from his just maintenance should go to the poor;<note place="margin">William Barret. Wil. Linnie. Th. Partington. Willi. Thomson.</note> and in the Certificate it is declared, that he had but twenty pound to shew: how little truth there is in their reports! for they have very slanderously given it out that the summe was at least twenty six pound, and that he had in a surreptitious way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted it all to his own use, that all the world may know what evil tongues they had, we did insert the particle, (but) we grudge not the poor, but wish we had more for them; and we think, that considering the poverty of our comparatively little society, there is more given to them then could be expected. It is a light thing with them in this time of their temptation and deep Apostasie, to judge of us, and to represent us to the world as persons not worthy to be trusted, neither Elders nor Deacons, with the receiving or distributing of such monies as come to our hands, unless we give an account to them, to what persons and in what proportion we have given what we have received, though it be six or seven years after. But when we are called unto it by those that have power, we doubt not but we shall be able to do it with good satisfaction; but through Gods grace the Church hath alwaies entertained better thoughts concerning us, and because they have judged us faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they have not rekoned with us from the time that we first united unto this day, according to what is asserted of some in Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12, 15. and <hi>chap.</hi> 22.7. and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 13.13.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154339:10"/>
                  <p>But they proceed to imagine falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to provoke the God of truth against themselves, they add sin to sin, one untruth unto another, while they say, none but <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> knew of the Letter written by Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> in Mr. <hi>Venables</hi> name; <hi>Edward Tipping</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Edw. Tipping.</note> and <hi>Iohn Wharm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John Wharmbee.</note> had also the knowledge of it, and all of them their direction from it, to dispose it as they did, before Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> received any part of it.<note place="margin">Edw. Tipping. Joh. Wharmbee. Tho. Newton.</note> Nor did Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> keep up the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for besides the Deacons, Mr. <hi>Iones</hi> saw it, and many others which cannot now particularly be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Nor was it for Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to keep it up; for the scope of Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> and Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> is thereby most clearely discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and serves to justifie both him and the Deacons above all other things. It appears by the Letter that it was contribution money that was sent, in the distribution of which there hath been alwaies an inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and a greater disproportion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times then in this money. A bare better half was never thought sufficient to maintain a preaching Ministry. The Church in its contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions looked mainly, if not solely, at them that were the teachers, and never interposed to abridge them, were grieved they could not aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them; but the ordering of them they left to the Deacons per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually without intermedling. The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154339:11"/> Letter was directed alone to Mr. <hi>Eat.</hi> who then should have the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereof but he? all that could be expected from him was but to shew it to such who were concerned in it, which were the Deacons prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, who were to act by it, and not the Church at all; yet wretched collections are made from it, as first, the Church would not have been so uncharitable as to make so unequal a division, when yet it never did nor doth meddle with divisions at all. Secondly, though it be not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Church-robbing, yet it was a covetous interposing in Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> betwixt the poor and the money; and why so? the onely reason that is rendred is this, because he had his own letter in his own keeping, and shewed it unto all who were concerned in it, and to some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides.</p>
                  <p>Nor had Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> direction been answered if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had barely had the better halfe, because Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> knew that contribution money (which he mentioned this to be) was not so divided, neither was it Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> direction to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider all that were poor and in debt first (for then Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> must have had nothing at all) but those brethren onely whose wants were exceeding pressing.<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi> Letter.</note> As for Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> of whom they say that he intended not that the money should be so divided, this we know that he had notice of it how it was divided, and declared himself well satisfied in it, and since this business was questioned. he said to <hi>William Barret,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>illiam Barret.</note> that if the Church (meaning the Deacons, for to them he sent his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154339:11"/> direction) had disposed of it all to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> he should not have been offended. And the truth is, amongst all that have contributed to the uses of the Church; not so much as one hath been found idterposing betwixt the Deacons and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their office by way of direction, in reference to what they have contibuted, but onely Colonell <hi>Venables</hi> in the one summe of mony, which hath occasioned all this contention, &amp;, as he saith in the other, though it be denied by the Deacon that received it. The conclusion which they make of this Section is very remarkable, after much complaining that Col. <hi>Venables</hi> his intention, and Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> his direction was not observed by the Deacons in the distribution of the money that was made by them, they bring an argument fetcht from the office of a Deacon, that the poor should have it all, and Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> none at all, by which they themselves would overturn and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly subvert and destroy the intention and direction of them both: For, say they (or he that hath formed this business for them) where find you that Deacons should have care of Church-officers? so would they say of all kind of maintenance, that no care at all might be had of it, either by Deacons or by any other, that all office and Ministry by that means might fall, no provision at all being made to support it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:154339:11"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>You are not ashamed to say that no speciall favour was shewed to Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, because it was according to the same rules of proportion you had formerly gone by, and that he had main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but what came through your hands: To which we answer,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154339:12"/> the more common an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is, the worse it is; and yet you say, that was your common rule, to make so unequall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions betwwixt Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and the poore: but did none of you know, or did not <hi>Tho. Newton</hi> know that M. <hi>Eaton</hi> had and hath an estate with his wife worth <hi>40 l. per an.</hi> or thereabouts? and that after the end of the first wars he had <hi>40. l per an.</hi> from se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questrations? and that he hath bought lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> to a good va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and either lands or rents in <hi>Cheshire</hi> worth <hi>34 l. per an.</hi> or thereabouts? and that he had forty or fifty pound as Chaplain to <hi>Chester</hi> Garrison, about <hi>1651.</hi> or did these or any of these come through your hands? If so, your sin was the greater, to give him twenty pound and to the poor but four, if they had it: and if he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154339:12"/> kept these or any of these secret from you, and pleaded necessity, was it not to keep you to your unequal division, to give five times so much to him as to all the poor of the Church? And why doe you so, since he hath no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to maintain, nor kept any house since he was your Pastor, which is about twelve yeares; but the nature of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse is, that much would have more; which more appears, because he hath now an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the State of an hundred pound <hi>per an.</hi> &amp; we querie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when he went to wait upon the L. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, then Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in Scotland, he had not an allowance from the Lord Generall, or else a levie upon the Church to defray his charge? yea, we querie whether he had not both; for we believe that the Lord Generall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154339:13"/> was so noble, that he would not let him serve him for nothing.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>Malice is ever working and is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unresonable, not admitting of an apology from them against whom it acts, how just soever: had it not been so with these persons, they would have been ashamed to argue so foolishly and perversely as they have done. If there be a fault, and that favour hath been shewed in this distribution to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> let it but appeare and we who are the Deacons wil bear the blame and the shame of it; but if we have kept to the old way, which hitherto we have walked in, and which delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154339:12"/> we took up, and which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers Congregationall principles, which you your selves, till cast out, have professed; why doe you raile thus upon us? If there must be teaching officers in a Church, then there must be suitable provision for them: For who goeth a warfare of his own charge? Such which preach the Gospel must live of the Gospel. Neither is there any iniquity in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributing with disproportion, when the persons which are distributed unto fal under a different considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and unequall distributions in such cases have the greatest equity in them. Doth any Steward distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the poor alike proportion of his Lords moneys as he doth to his Lords labourers, or hired servants? or which of these persons having work-folks, doth give unto the poor as they give unto them, unlesse they know they have enough for both? Will they put difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their hired servants and the poor, dispensing their bread and money with disproportion? and do they cavill at us, and brand us with unrighteousnesse for carrying our distributions in like manner? Shall not we have as much care of the Lords labours as they have of their own? They would closely insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as if there were a robbing of the poor in this distribution, but they dare not speak out. But shall we rob the Lords servants that worke in his vineyard for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154339:12"/> sake of the poore? or doth this high contest for the poor, in which they so greatly vilifie us, arise out of that tender respect they bear to the poor, and not rather from their spleen and rage against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> &amp; envy against Ministry? For do not we know that for many years the one of these left off contributing,<note place="margin">Edw. Tipping. James Johnson. Joh. Wharmbie. Tho. Newton.</note> and the other never came up to it (so far as we remember) or if he did, he soon desisted; by which means neither officers nor poor have received that which hath been right; and what they will call this let them consider.</p>
                  <p>But they would bear themselves out in theier unreasonable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just accusation of us, by minding us what an estate Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> hath by his wife; which were it true, (as it is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry false, for instead of 40 l. <hi>per annum</hi> he hath not made (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self saith, and some know) 30 l. of clear profit) yet it is not to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, for the labourer is worthy of his hire, notwithstanding any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per personall estate he hath of his own. And we do assert, that at that time when we alotted this 20 l. to M. <hi>Eat.</hi> he had not any allowance for preaching, but what came through our hands, which at that time was not 28 l. <hi>per an.</hi> for what h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had from <hi>Chester</hi> was while Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> was with us, who divided it with him, and was soon at an end, and was some yeares before 1651. and what he had from sequestrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154339:13"/> which was also in Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> time, and ceased long before the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned yeare of 1651. was (while he enjoyed it) but the half part of 32. <hi>l.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">That the profits that came from the State, and the purchases that were made, were either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after <hi>51.</hi> these witnesses: Will. Barret. R. Warmingsham James Walker. Joh. Wharmbie. Tho. Newton. Th. Partington. Will. Thomson, and many more.</note> As for his purchases that in <hi>Irleand</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable, yielding trouble without profit. These persons that mention it may ask their friends which have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt with him whether they ever received one pennie: and as it is yet at present (if duely paid) his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oportion would be under 10. <hi>l. per ann.</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rchase made at this time when this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was given to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> but several years after; and that purchase in <hi>Cheshire</hi> was made very lately, and a mistake there is in the valuing of it, which being so frequent in this Paper we wonder not at; not hath he acted cunningly to hide any of these things, if he had, he might habe escaped the scourge of these mens tongues and pens, who are watching for all advantages to render him odious; and though he ha h not children, he hath had, and yet hath kindred which have and do fetch much from his estate: and if he hath not kept house, the weakness <hi>of his wife (who of long time hath been infirme) and more especially of late) and her desire to be freed from cares (being indeed unfit for them which do necessarily attend house-keeping) hath been the reason,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">William Barret. Tho. Partington Will. Thomson. Wil. Linnie. Joh. Wharmbie. Tho. Gellibrand Tho. Goodier. John Bagly. Pet. Fearnhead. Tho. Birch. John Harrison. Ralph Bagly, and all others of the Church that have been with us.</note>
                     <hi>and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of greater estate, and in other respects, more fit, have yet without any scandal upon them lived in the same way: nor was he ever ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rged with covetousness (so far as we have heard, unless it were by some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular person, which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d a mind to asperse him without cause before this time: But malice and spleen will ever find faults; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s wife hath said many times (and those that are acquainted with her know her to be of a free spirit and not covetous) that more is spent in the way they now live in, and by giving where need requires, then would keep house in good manner; and what a pattern of forwardness he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th been in the Church upon all occasions of contribution, and how he hath excited us to every good work of that kind, and been presidential unto us therein, when any poor have been to be relieved, we can all testifie: but it is a light and easie thing for these persons to disparage others, what worth soever may be in them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That he hath now an allowance of 100. <hi>l. per an.</hi> is as false as the rest,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, so many as were mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at that time are witnesses al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so against the Leavy.</note>
                     <hi>and if he had it, he might be thought to deserve it as well as many others that have it; that of a levy from the Church to defray the charge of his journey to <hi>Scotland</hi> is a nevv business, and united in the brain of those that delight in lies, for there vvas no such thing: and the one of these persons cannot choose but knovv it, and both of them might have informed themselves better before they had publlshed it, that the Lord Protector then General that called him thither did nobly revvard him, hath alvvaies been thankfully ackcovvledged by him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154339:13"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>If the Letter from Mr. <hi>Tayler</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, why did ye not print it; for if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> ever be cleared, it is that must do it, and not your peece-meale Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, under which wit and words, may make a truth seeme a lie, and a lye seeme a truth. And who knowes your Author, knowes he is both ful of wit and words, to extenuate or aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate to his own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est temptation in publique, being cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and private, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which meeting together, are like the sonnes of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> too hard for a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> without the help of a heavenly power, which Mr. <hi>Tayler</hi> conceived to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you, as by his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154339:14"/> charitable caution, appeares of fully di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributing to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> if the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of private bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding pressing. And if it be the goodness of God, that the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is extant, why was it not discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, before the money came in question? which though it was sent in <hi>1651.</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known to the Church (as we could heare of) till <hi>1656.</hi> And that it should be now discovered, is so remarkable, as that it bespeakes it selfe to be the just hand of God, that others may feare and tremble, and beware of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous under dealing. For truth seekes no corners, but no cause of feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to us, as you falsly apply it, unless for your and his unrighteous dealings.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154339:14"/> And the aforesaid <hi>Will. Barret</hi> saith yet, that he did not know of the money. And at that time there was no Elder but he and Mr. <hi>Eaton.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154339:13"/>
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>As for Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> Letter, which they again speak of, they know it is extant, for they saw it, and heard it read in the presence of Collonel <hi>Venables,</hi> and we printed a part of it, and left out the principal part of it, (which was that Collonel <hi>Venables</hi> sent the money to supply the want of his contribution, in that time of his absence) to our own great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, so far are we from cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Artifices in acting in our own affaires; and that letter doth fully cleare both Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> and they have heard it read, (as was said before) and yet cease not to calumniate: What hope therefore of convincing them by printing it? And yet before that letter was found the <hi>Deacons</hi> declaring, that they had seen such a letter, and that they had according to it, awarded such mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> (which was in a Church meeting) the Church was generally satisfied therewith,<note place="margin">Will. Barr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> W. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap> Will. Linn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> T Partington Jo. Wharmby Edw. Hall, J. Sydebottom and many more persons might be named.</note> and of all that were present, there was only one man, (the one of these two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>viz. Robert Ridgway,</hi>) that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed himself unsatisfied, to the great offence of the rest, in these words, <hi>Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>hath made a l ng story, but he is not cleared for all this.</hi> And the Letter being found, Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> gave witness to it, and hath many times declared Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and us to be without blame in that busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154339:14"/> &amp; at the <hi>Northwich,</hi> where the one of these persons was,<note place="margin">Thomas Partington Ja. Johnson. Tho. Newton Rob. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingsham.</note> who had accused Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, in receiving that money, and whether also the other came the next meeting, after there had been a full and faire hearing, before Baron <hi>Bruen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fisher,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Angier,</hi> which were Commissioners appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to examine differences about sums of money, Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was cleared, and the Authours and Fomenters of these slanders, exhorted to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">The Paper under the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hands declares so much.</note> for scandalizing a Servant of Jesus Christ, and Minister of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel. And this Letter of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Taylers</hi> was read at that time, and two of the <hi>Deacons</hi> took their Oaths, that they acted according to the known rules of distributing in other cases, and a third <hi>Deacon</hi> was at <hi>London</hi> at that time, but confirmed the same by oath at the next meeting, so that neither words nor wit carried this matter but truth and uprightness, so that if these persons had not been of a bad resolved spirit, and given up to love and speak falshood rather then truth, they would not have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the judgement of these Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, and after their determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, have published so false and wicked a Pamphlet.</p>
                  <p>And though they do again accuse Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> to be ambitious, after credit in publique, and covetous of of profit in private, and make these two to be like the two Sonnes of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154339:14"/>
                     <hi>Zerviah,</hi> too hard for a <hi>David,</hi> without the help of a heavenly power, (which we hope Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> through the help of an heavenly power, will reap great advantage by at the last:) yet we must say,<note place="margin">William Barret Will. Thompson Will. Linny Will. Thomson Edw. Tip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing Iohn Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmby Tho. Newton. Ja. Johnson Edw. Hall Tho Hughes Jo Sydebottom James Holme, and very many others.</note> that if these two evills be so predominant in him, he hath not taken the course he might have taken, to satisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in either; for he hath had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations to preach in great and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique places, and offers of hundreds made unto him, where he might have had applause and profit, and yet hath rather chosen to sit down in a corner with a few despised ones, and to accept of small things, then to leave us.</p>
                  <p>And for the Letter of Mr. <hi>Tayler,</hi> upon which they harp so much, it was discovered to the <hi>Deacons</hi> and others, as we have declared, and might have been to the Church, had there been any reason for it, long before the money came into question; yea, before received, and was lost again amongst a multitude of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, till searched out by M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eaton,</hi> upon the rumour of this money got abroad to his reproach. And though every thing be worthy to be observed, which the Lord permits to be, because a wise godly heart, will fetch profit out of it; yet it is not strange, that envy should work upon words spoken, (as <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> asserted, and these persons witnessed from her mouth,) by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollonel <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> not so considerately, though perhaps not at all at that time,<note place="margin">William Barret Tho Partington Wil. Linny Wil. Thomson Edw. Tipping Jo. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmby Tho. New<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Iohnson Edw. Hall Ralph Dick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enson, and very many more.</note> with any evil intention to give advantage to others. <hi>I sent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies from Ireland,</hi> said Collonel <hi>Venables, hadst thou thy share in it?</hi> And again, <hi>I sent the money to the Church, and not to Mr. Eaton</hi> not remembring (it may be) what direction he had given to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Tayler,</hi> to write such a Letter. These were the words, and these words it seemes, administred matter to <hi>Joyce Hall,</hi> and to these two persons, through an old grudge harboured in their hearts against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> to asperse him with unrighteousness, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Sum of money. From which to cleare himself, he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through his papers, and at last met with this Letter of Mr. <hi>Taylers,</hi> and produced it for his own justification, and appealed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154339:15"/> to the <hi>Deacons,</hi> whether from the direction they took from it, they had not ordered such monies to him. And there is cause of trembling, to consider, that malice should work so mightily in persons, where much of Religion hath been thought to be (es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the one of them) as to render them uncapable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving satisfaction, after so full and clear a representation of things made unto them. And that they should dare to print such a Pamphlet, after so publique a tryal, which this matter received at <hi>Northwich.</hi> As for <hi>William Barret,</hi> his saying that he did not know of the money, we all understand how deeply his memory is charged with multiplicity of affaires, and if his memory faile him, it is not to be wondred at, after so long time elapsed. They know it fayld him in a matter of moment, when he said, <hi>That he was not in such a place at such a time,</hi> and yet was a principal actor at that time, in that place as was confessed on all hands.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:154339:15"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>Whereas you say, we have since been divided among our selves, with high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to heaven, it is an untruth, for we were never divided; as for <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> that told us, we leave her to answer for her self, who spake truth in the main, and if it had been a mistake in her, tis no ground for you to boast in anothers infirmity, except you free your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154339:15"/> selves: It is true, we did appeal to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and so we can yet do, that what we testified was truth; for we testified no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> told us, and did not assert that the report was truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forewarned by <hi>William Barrett</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> did not so much matter the businesse of the money so he could entrap us. And if it were so hain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in <hi>Joyce Hall,</hi> to contradict her self, what was it in Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> to contradict himself twice in one thing, with high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to heaven; and afterward, when wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses were ready to have proved the thing, then and not before to confesse the truth? Is not this matter of trembling.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>Concerning their being divided, which they quarrel at, the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate saith, that the persons that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised and first reported these mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous untruths were divided amongst themselves, and so it was. They say, it is an untruth, for they were never divided; here is pretty juggling: they mean, they two were never divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor was that asserted, but <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> comes in with them as a third person in the Certificate, and she and they were divided; she against them, and they against her. They say, she told them so, and she saith, she told them not so, but that they imagined it themselves, and then cast it upon her. They appeal to heaven, and she ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to heaven; and their appeals
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154339:15"/> are in that wherein they contradict each other: And where is then the untruth that we have told, must it not be laid at their own door? And is it not remarkable, and may cause trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, for these were three friends, all of them deeply discontented against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and watching for advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And one reports to the other two, something grosse and bad in Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> as was apprehended, and they readily receive it, and divulge it, and it comes to this at last, that a grosse lie was told amongst them, which was manifest, and did stare them in the face; then they divide, which were one before, and there is affirming and denying one against the other with dreadful words, and a fourth comes in to help her that was alone and was over-matched, and turnes the scale, being not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but a witnesse. Was not this the hand of God, that they should be thus confounded, while they were thus maliciously acting against Mr. <hi>Eaton?</hi> But their enmity against him hath reconciled them altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And this appears in that they say of her, that she spake truth in the main, and that it was a mistake and her infirmity. Which are but fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves to cover their own shame, for it was they that invented it, and the thing consisted not in the change of some words, which might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake, but in the addition of many words, which were never spoken, and it was the main thing, for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154339:16"/> had it been true, the unrighteousnesse of Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> would much have appeared. But they are forced at last to confesse a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in her, (and why not in themselves rather) and would take away the foulness of it, by presenting a more grosse and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous contradiction in Mr. <hi>Eaton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This contradiction is one of those lying charges which was contained in a paper of <hi>Thomas Wirrall</hi> read in the presence of the Church, after he had renounced his membership; for which and for many other grosse miscarriages he was cast out.</p>
                  <p>The thing was thus, at a private meeting of Elders and some other persons, <hi>Thomas Wirrall,</hi> and <hi>John Bruckshaw</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> spake these words, That if all in the Church were like to some, he should count it as great a mercy as could come unto him, to leave the Church. To which words no reply was made. At the next Church-meeting <hi>Thomas Wirral</hi> brings in a charge against Mr <hi>Eaton,</hi> mentioning some of his words, and adding others of his own, <hi>viz. unlesse the Church would clear him he would leave them, and should account it a mercy so to do.</hi> Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> peremptorily denyed such expressions, granted some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but not all as was presented, but neither he nor any that were present at the other conference (<hi>John Bruckshaw</hi> being absent) could remember what the words were that were spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. After this there was another Church meeting appointed, at which <hi>John Bruckshaw</hi> was present; but before the day came,<note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll. Barrett. Will Linny Edw. Tipping. Will. Thomson. Tho: Newton Iohn Sydebottom Tho. Goodier. Tho. Birch. Iohn Wharmby Hugh Eccles.</note> the very words that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> spake were brought to his mind, which he acquainted several persons with, and on that day, <hi>John Bruckshaw</hi> read the very self-same words out of a paper which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had before mentioned to be his words, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his reading of them Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> owned them as his, and this was the contradiction which is charged upon him. A most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible abuse, worthy to be punished by a Judge, is herein put upon him, and we are many of us witnesses hereof. That which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects <hi>William Barret</hi> we are not able to say any thing to, but leave it to him to make his own answer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:154339:16"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>You say two of us have since for that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154339:16"/> and other miscarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges been cast out of the Church. Why do you adde this, but to cast a vail before the eyes of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to make him think, that your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse of so great an Ordinance will clear your innocency? What you charged us with, given since under your hands, make us not the subjects of excommunication, as we shall shew in time and place. But it seems, that this disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the money was the main thing for which, and also for other miscarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of yours, we had rather be out then in. Your casting us out was but to cast an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um upon us, for just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaving of you, and to cover some naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of your own you apprehended would appear to your shame. So that when Mr.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154339:17"/>
                  <hi>Eaton</hi> is cleared, we shall so certifie with you, but not till then; and not till then, nor then we proved ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators. But is not <hi>William Barret</hi> aforesaid rather a Calumniator? Who certifies thus now? And yet since <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 6. 1656.</hi> came to us and desired us to appear in the disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of this money, and promised to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond us therein: and wished us to stay a while before we broke off, that he might go out with us, time would not be so long.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>We have indeed presented it to the worlds view, that these two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons have been cast out of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154339:16"/> Church for that and other miscarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that the world might know what spirits are abroad, and how great Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> sufferings have been from unthankful and unworthy persons; and to shew what a sense the Church notwithstanding hath had of his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightness and innocencie, in that they have thought themselves obliged to vindicate him, by a just censure past upon his unrighteous accusers. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which we have charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on these persons make them justly the subjects of excommunication or not, might have been brought unto tryal long since, as they know, if they would either have condescended that godly men of sound principles, of the Congregational way, or of the Presbyterian judgement, might have had the hearing of it. And very lately at <hi>Northwich,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath informed us, the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Baron Bevin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fisher,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Angier,</hi> intreated Colonel <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> to go unto them, and to make the like proposal unto them again, but all in vain; their answer was, they would think of it, as they have said before; but it appeared that their resolution was, that they will either have men that are of corrupt and rotten principles to have the hearing of it, or they will have none at all. And they have found it the safest course for them to plead their cause in print, and to blast the reputations of others that way, then to bring it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154339:17"/> before upright and unbyassed Judges. for by that meanes their false and slanderous assertions and aspersions may escape a just tryal.</p>
                  <p>And for the discovery of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which they say was the main thing for which they were cast out; we answer, that it is notoriously false, nor was it any cause at all, nor was there any thing of truth discovered about it, which any of us had a mind should be kept secret; but there is much untruth and falshood discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in these persons, which have made all this noise about it, which might justly fill their faces with shame, &amp; for which with other things they have been justly laid under that dreadful sentence of excommunication, and so they are like to continue out of the Church till the Lord be pleased kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to humble them, which in his own time (if they belong unto him) he will do.</p>
                  <p>Their leaving of us was to prevent their own being cast out, which they saw was hastning upon them; for we had long been exercised under the distemper of their spirits (which the Messengers of the Church upon a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> discourse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>one discerned, and offences were more and more multiplied, so that there was at last no remedy but to cut them off from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Lords people, among whom they were wont to walk and to partake of holy Ordinances. The con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deration of which (were their consciences awakened) might be v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry affrighti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g to their spirits.</p>
                  <p>And now seeing that after such a cloud of darkness, which through mischievous tongues lay upon Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> his name, God hath been pleased to shew mercy, and make the light of truth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154339:17"/> break forth▪ and so clear him from such unjust imputations of u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness in reference to this sum of money which they have made all this stirre about; and also in reference to another sum mentioned in some of the Certificates, they may do well to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member what they have here promised, to wit, to certifie with us, how unjust they have been against him and us, and how justly we have proceeded against them.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>William Barrett,</hi> we leave him again to make his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> answer, not thinking it meet to meddle with that which they say privately passed from him to them, not knowing but that they may be as injurious against him in their relating things as we have found (to our grief and their shame) they have been to us.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154339:17"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>Your spirit of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that told you we had a grudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was a spirit of false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, for we had none against him. And how can you say, it was for endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to heal our souls, when one of us had answered your <hi>21.</hi> sifting Articles to your satisfaction, and you never laid any thing to either of our charge, nor admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, until one of us had admonished you, and admonished not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154339:18"/> the other, till the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was questioned, and then for no er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in doctrine, nor scandal in conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but because he would not tell you whether he told them (whom you call un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly your professed enemies) of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and would not (as you say) be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied about the money.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>Whether these persons had a grudge against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Eaton</hi> doth not require any special spirit of discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to determine it; nor have we professed to have any such spirit, to give them occasion to say it is a spirit of falshood. It was manifest to all within the Church,<note place="margin">Will. Barret T. Partington W. Thomson Will. Linnie Jo. Wharmby Edward Tipping. Edw. Hall, J. Sydebottom Ja: Holme. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Hughes Ralph Dickenson. John W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rberton.</note> who we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of things; and were unbyassed, that it was so, for he was the person that continually they struck at, and hardly any thing could be spoke or done by him, but they gathered mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of offence from it to themselves. And the hard speeches that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y have uttered in the eares of some of us upon all occasions aga nst him, have witnessed how they have st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od affected towards him. But now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h y have made it obvious to the world, what a spirit of malignity they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their searching into all things,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154339:18"/> and their evil surmising where they can know nothing, and their wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perverting things against him, and their striving by all meanes, even u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to the frequent violating of truth, to make him faulty, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it.</p>
                  <p>And it was for endeavouring to heal their soules,<note place="margin">The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d persons g ve witnesse to this also.</note> for distemper had (for some time) been growing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and some temptations had taken hold on them; the publick Ordinance had not been so much frequented, nor private Communion kept up, but much remissenesse there was, and their spirits grew very high and troublesome, and if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> reproved it was not accepted, so that he hath been forced some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make knowne the trouble of his heart to others.</p>
                  <p>And though they say (to smooth the matter over, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move suspition from the Reader) that the one of them answered to the one and twenty sifting Questions, yet we know that the one of them is against baptizing of Infants,<note place="margin">Will. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> singing of Psalmes, against which reproachfull expressions have been used (as used in the Churches of the Saints) an instituted Ministry and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as dispensed by Pastors and Teachers, and withheld his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution upon that account,<note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll: Linny Tho: Partington W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll: Thomson J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. Warmby</note> declaring that when M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Eaton</hi> could prove himselfe a Minister, so indued with power from on high, as the Ministers of Christ were in the primitive times, then he would acknowledge those Scriptures to be in force, in reference to him, which speake of Ministers maintenance; Nor doth he acknowledge any such power now in the Church of delivering up to Satan, as the Apostle speaks of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. And as for the other, he is not right in his Judgement, nor laudable in his walking, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is cast out we shall let him alone.</p>
                  <p>And though there was a slownesse in the Church in setting upon them a solemne admonition, yet the offences were many which were committed by them, of which we warned them oft,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154339:18"/> and with much patience laboured to have healed them, therefore it is most untruly represented, that we never laid any thing to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their charge, before the one of these admonished us, which gentlenesse, was at last so greatly abused by the one of them,<note place="margin">William Barret Will. Linny Tho, Parting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on Will. Thomson. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mby E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w: Hall. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Sydebo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Tho. Hughes and very many more.</note> that when the Church reprooved him, he had the impudence to admonish the Church; And in reference to the other of them, when the divulging of untruths against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Eaton,</hi> was added to many former offences, and being charged with it, and one place mentioned where it was done; when there was perversenesse found in him, and the thing would neither be confessed, nor deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there was then a solemne admonition set upon him for all his miscarriages together, wherein we conceive we discharged a duty, and offended not.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:154339:18"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>The righteous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of God will be more clearly beheld, if he enable you to give glory to him, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the truth of what you know, of your own knowledge, and not what you were taught by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, For by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Style, the Author may easily be discerned.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>If the righteous proceedings of God may more clearly be beheld by enabling us to give glory to God, by certifying the truth of what we know of our own knowledge, then through Gods grace we can and will give glory to God; for we will certify the truth as it is in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, which is this.</p>
                  <p>In the latter end of the yeare,<note place="margin">Tho. Newton Ed: Typing. Iohn Wharmby</note> 1651, a letter directed to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Eaton</hi> came from M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Taylor</hi> in Colonell <hi>Ven ables</hi> name; in which 24. <hi>li.</hi> was mentioned as sent by him for contribution money, with speciall direction to the Deacons, to consider M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Eaton,</hi> and this money was to be got in by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Eatons</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry, and we were acquainted with all this very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oon after the receit of this letter; and thereupon ordered that M<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
                     <hi>Eaton</hi> should have 20 <hi>li.</hi> of it, and the poor the rest, before any penny of it was received! for the letter came over without the money, which was to be received as it could be got. And this we did with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154339:19"/> much uprightness of spirit, apprehending that it was most suitable to the rule of righteousnesse, and did most answer the mind of the Donor; And there was nothing of privacy intended by any of us, in this transaction.</p>
                  <p>And we do now further certify, that God may have the glory of it, and that they may have the shame of it, (if by that means they may be brought unto repentance) that they have most groundlessely, and unjustly, made a great stirre and bussle about this matter, and have by their evill surmises and many grosse un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, laboured to possesse the minds of men, with an evill opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, both of ours, and Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> honest, direct, and above-board dealings, to the great dishonour of God, defamation of Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and reproach of us who are the <hi>Deacons;</hi> And that they have great cause to be deeply humbled befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e God, for these their miscarriages, and whatsoever they collect from the rigour or equivocation of the style, wherein they grossely abuse Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> whose plainnesse doth testify for him, that he is a stranger, (as we beleeve, to equivocation, &amp; which we also have in detestation, yet our Certificate is not guilty of it. And we do assert, that we have not been taught by Mr. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aton</hi> or any other, to speake or act any thing contrary to the truth, as it is in our Consciences.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154339:19"/>
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>For Colonell <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables</hi> Certificate about the <hi>24. li.</hi> we shall say nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, but it may be true, and yet Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> never the more cleared thereby; for the necessity of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Brethren should have been first consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, before Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> should have had any part of it, which both the letter
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154339:19"/> and the Certificate do testifie.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>There is much false-dealing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenting things out of the letter &amp; Certificate, they do concut (indeed) and both speak of very pressing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities of Brethren, and these per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons leave out the words: <hi>very pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing,</hi> and <hi>exceeding pressing.</hi> They both say that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> should be very fully considered, if necessities be not exceeding pressing, and these persons change it and say, <hi>that necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties must be first considered before Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>be considered at all or have any part of it.</hi> If they had said that very pressing necessities must be first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, before he had had any full part of it, they had said the truth, but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154339:19"/> as they have expressed it,, it is a lye instead of truth.</p>
                  <p>And some other words which are in Mr <hi>Taylers</hi> Letter are left out in their mentioning of it, to wit, <hi>That the moneys sent by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel Venables was to supply the defect of his contribution in the time of his absence;</hi> on purpose (as may be feared) to darken the truth. For the words carry great light in them unto the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifying of Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> in all that he hath received, and of the Deacons in all that they have alotted. But enough hath been said of this already.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answer.</head>
               <p>We shall leave it to the judgement of the impartial Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to whom the charges of lying, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, fomenting, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious slandering, endeavoured by the Certificates to be cast upon us, doth of right belong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 6.</hi> Vntruth in these words.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:154339:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Deceipt and fraud.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 7.</hi> Vntruth in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Deceit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to a lie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 8.</hi> Vntruth in saying that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth, in saying that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth and a scoffe in saying that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 9.</hi> Sinfull shifting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> False sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, which is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent to an untruth in saying.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:154339:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 10.</hi> Vntruth in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in these words; spoken of the Deacons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Great deceit in inquiring why the Particle <hi>(But)</hi> was put in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Evil sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander and untruth in saying.</p>
               <p>And in saying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 11.</hi> Vntruth in saying.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154339:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Malice in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Malice and perversenesse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Wicked sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 12.</hi> Evil sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in these words.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154339:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Malice in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Evil sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise equivalent to a grosse untruth in the Querie they make.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Evill sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander again in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander yet again in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 13.</hi> Malice and slander in a high degree in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander again of high nature in these words.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:154339:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Deceit in these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander of the highest and most dreadful kind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 14.</hi> Deceit in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth and slander in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth and slander in these words</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Slander in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page 15.</hi> Vntruth and slander.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> Vntruth in saying.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>And now seeing they commit all to the impartial Reader to judge of, if their representation of things had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en without impartiality, they might have done it with more honour and comfort. But having abused the Reader all along with false and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entations, they have disabled him from making a right judgement, and if he make any judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all from what they have declared he must see cause (we doubt not) having read this reply to recall it.</p>
                  <p>By what hath been presented the Reader may easily discerne, that their Answer to the Certificates doth either wholly, or for the most part consist of deceit, untruth, slander, evil surmising, sinful shifting, scorning, malice.</p>
                  <p>Consider the several pages, and it will appear.</p>
                  <p>Our desires are not to cast aspersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the persons of others, when yet they took up the report of <hi>Joyce Hall,</hi> and addeth thereto, and divulged it, by which Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> came to be much aspersed.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:154339:20"/>
                  <p>Witnesse the relation which they make of the discourse betwixt <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> and themselves.</p>
                  <p>None of the persons you intend in the Certificates did ever mention 28 <hi>l.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When they ask, whether it be a grosse lie to testifie what they were informed of, when yet they knew that they were charged with lying, not for testifying what they were informed of, but for speaking what they were not informed of, but had forged and divised.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Will. Barret</hi> and <hi>Katharine Ashton</hi> declared, that <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had cleared them.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> confessed, that the 24 <hi>l.</hi> was sent to the Church, and not to him, and that he wrote to Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> and by that means altered his mind, and got the money.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> said, if he might not take the money upon that account, yet he might upon this account. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Venables</hi> his former Wife gave two shillings six pence each Lords day, which computed will come to four and twenty pounds since she dyed.</p>
                  <p>Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> had paid for a dead Wife.</p>
                  <p>They mention Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> his sending F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrs to hide the lie, which was told when they reported, that he had sent other moneys to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> to cut him off from claiming any part in the four and twenty pounds which he sent.</p>
                  <p>The Deacons were not acquainted with the money which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent unto their dispose.</p>
                  <p>They believe that none of the Deacons, but <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> knew of the money.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:154339:20"/>
                  <p>All the Deacons, except <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> said, that they never heard or knew of the money.</p>
                  <p>You formerly denied it.</p>
                  <p>They might have known why; It was to discover an untruth, that they were guilty of in reporting that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had taken all the money that Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> sent, when yet it was but 20 <hi>li.</hi> They would not seem to know it that they might abuse us by it.</p>
                  <p>It is not known what poor had the three pound, nor who had the other twenty shillings; this is of the nature of a high slander.</p>
                  <p>None of the Deacons knew of the Letter.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> kept the Letter in his own custody both from the Deacons and the Church.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> therefore did it because he knew Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> directions were not that he should have 20 <hi>li.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though we call it not Church rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, yet it was a covetous interposing betwixt the poor and the money.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> directions had been observed if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had had the better half of the money sent.</p>
                  <p>Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> intended not the money should have been so divided. For he intended it should be div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ded, as in discretion the Deacons should do it, for he committed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t to them.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154339:21"/>
                  <p>If committed to the Deacons, all should have gone to the poor, because Deacons are for the poor: But where find you that they are for Church Officers? In this appears an evil eye; they have grudgings against that they knew Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> intended him.</p>
                  <p>You are not ashamed to say, <hi>You shewed no favour:</hi> herein they make favour, not righteousnesse, to be the rule observed by us the Deacons in our dividing, and us shamelesse in denying it.</p>
                  <p>They strive to make us guilty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all reason, we plead we have acted, according to old known rules, deliberately and justly agreed upon at first, and yet we must be guilty.</p>
                  <p>In the value that they put upon Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> estate which he hath by his Wife.</p>
                  <p>In the forty pounds <hi>pey annum</hi> spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, as received by Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> from sequestrations.</p>
                  <p>In mentioning what Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> purchased in the value, and especially in the time.</p>
                  <p>In applying the forty or fifty pounds received as Chaplain to <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> Garrison, especially in reference to the time, for it was long before.</p>
                  <p>They speak of four pounds to the poor, and adde these words, <hi>If they had it,</hi> meaning, if they were not cheated of it.</p>
                  <p>If Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> kept close these things, and pleaded necessity, was it not to keep you to your unequal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154339:21"/>
                  <p>And why do you so, seeing he hath no children, and hath kept no house since he was Pastor, these twelve years, herein they shew a spirit of envy, all is too much that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him.</p>
                  <p>But the nature of covetousness is, that much would have more.</p>
                  <p>He hath now an allowance from the State of one hundred pound <hi>per annum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whether there was not a Levie from the Church for his j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urney to <hi>Scotland?</hi> When yet the one of them knows the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Your piece meal Collections, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which wit and words may make a truth seem a lie, and a lie seem a truth.</p>
                  <p>Who knows your Author! (they mean Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi>) knows he is both full of wit and words, to extenuate or aggravate to his own advantage.</p>
                  <p>His greatest temptation in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, being credit, and in private, profit.</p>
                  <p>If it be the goodnesse of God, that the Letter is extant, why was it not discovered before the money came in question?</p>
                  <p>That it should be now discovered being sent in 1651. bespeaks a just hand of God, that others may fear and tremble and beware of covetous under-dealing.</p>
                  <p>No cause of fear and trembling to us, unlesse it be for your and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous dealing.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:154339:22"/>
                  <p>We were never divided, that is, not we two, <hi>Robert Ridgway</hi> and <hi>John Bruckshaw,</hi> but you three, <hi>Robert Ridgway, Iohn Bruckshaw,</hi> and <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> were divided, of which the Certificate speaks, as you know.</p>
                  <p>In charging contradiction, (with appeals to God) upon Mr. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They will shew in due time, that they were not the subjects of <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> when yet they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided motions of hearing, unlesse men unsound in judgement might be their Judges.</p>
                  <p>The discovery of the money was the main cause of <hi>excommunication;</hi> Their conscience knows otherwise: <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> first mentioned the money to them, and yet she is not cast out.</p>
                  <p>Your c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sting out, was but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>st an odium for justly leaving you, and to cover some nakednesse of your own.</p>
                  <p>Your spirit of discerning is a spirit of falsehood.</p>
                  <p>You never laid any thing to our charge, untill one of us had▪ admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished you.</p>
                  <p>They intimate that we were taught by another to say that in our Certifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate, which was not truth in our own conscience.</p>
                  <p>The Certificate and Letter testifie, that the necessities of private Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren must first be considered of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was to have any part of the money sent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:154339:22"/>
            <head>A Copy of the Letter sent from Mr. <hi>Tayler,</hi> endorsed thus. <hi>To my deare Brother, Mr.</hi> Samuel Eaton, <hi>Teacher to the Church of</hi> Duckenfield, <hi>these with trust deliver.</hi> And within directed to the Elders and Deacons of the Church of <hi>Duckenfield.</hi> So much of it as concerneth this present business.</head>
            <p>MY Colonel and our deare Brother, being this day to take a journey, desired me to write to you, and to assigne 24. <hi>l.</hi> to be payd by <hi>Thomas Bickerstaffe</hi> of <hi>Priston,</hi> as part of 68 <hi>l.</hi> due to me, for the use of the Church, and to supply the defect of his Contribution in this time of his absence, promising to pay the same Summe to me here, and it is his desire to the <hi>Deacons,</hi> that if the necessities of private members, be not exceeding pressing, that they would very fully distribute to my Brother <hi>Eaton,</hi> and the rather, because that after my removal, and when the Church had but one Teaching Officer to maintain, my Brother <hi>Eatons</hi> maintenance was not so honourable, as we hoped it would have been, unlesse I have been misinformed.</p>
            <p>My Colonel is desirous that my Brother <hi>Eaton</hi> should call for the money, and take my receipt, to deliver to <hi>Thomas Bickerstaffe,</hi> because happily he will most reverence him, and be most afraid to put him off with delayes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Worrall,</hi> his Answer to the <hi>Certificate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the better understanding of it, the Reader may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that in a paper that is now in our hands, <hi>Thomas Worrall</hi> makes such a charge against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> that he or his Agents for him, pleading want, thereby got that money which was at first intended for the poor, <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> knowing that it reflected
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154339:23"/> upon him in his Certificate, saith thus. And whereas it is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged maliciously by some, that he, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Agents for him pleaded want, and did thereby get such monies to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I do hereby assert, that I spake not one word of want, but only said, that he had lately borrowed money, which was a truth. Nor did Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> wish me to speak such words: nor did he know that I spake any such words till I told him, nor did Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> make any mention of the poor.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Thomas Worrall</hi> returnes this Answer.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>When Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> brought 10 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived (as in truth it was) and as himself saith, that it was contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on money, because it was a long time since he had given any; and knowing that if so, then Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> would have a great share therein, he said innocently, as we have cause to believe, without any design, that it came seasonably as to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> for he had lately borrowed money; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Venables</hi> his answer was such, as made him think that indeed he brought it for him; for he said, he was glad it came so seasonably for him, and declared no other use, and thereupon <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> gave it to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> as left for him, not knowing of any alteration, (if there were any) in the Colonels purpose, occasioned by his words; for the Colonel declared not so much, but left it for him, as he hath said since▪ For this <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> was at first called Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> Agent, <hi>viz.</hi> one that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had imployed, (for such a one is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly an Agent) and one that by pleading Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> want or necessity, had changed Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> mind, and got that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which was intended for the poor</p>
                  <p>Now though this do appear to be false (for Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> never
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154339:23"/> imployed him, nor knew that he spake any thing) yet still he must be an Agent, a voluntary Agent, and that is made to be the worst kind of Agent. Truly such perverting and wresting, and misinterpreting mens upright honest and harmless expressions and actions, and publishing the same to take away their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is sufficient to put Towns, Countries, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths into Combustion, and to take away peace from the Earth. And because it doth appear that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> received not this money, but as it was delivered to him, (as left for him) by the Deacon <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> that received it from Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> it is sufficient alone to acquit Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> from guile about it, but as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, who is able to stand before envie?</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Answer.</head>
                     <p>It is cleare from you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> own Certificate, that you was the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to get Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> the money, though he might not bid you, nor know of it till you gave it him, so that his not imploying you, makes you a voluntary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, which is so much worse on your part.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>If <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> used not the word (want) why then did he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish so great an untruth in his paper which he read before the Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and him, in which these words are found <hi>(he or his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents pleading want)</hi> nor is it of stronger import to say, <hi>such a one hath lately borrowed money,</hi> then to sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>such a one is in want.</hi> For it may be any mans case to borrow money, upon some occasion, and not be in want or poverty. Nor will any wise man stick to borrow money of a Friend, though it be to buy Land, or rent, if there be a considerable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why he should do it. And if he have of his own wherewith to do it, though perhaps not all of it, in such readiness, which was Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> case. Nor were any such words u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed as an Argument to get Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> that money, but an apprehension that that money at least was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154339:24"/> intended for him, caused those words to be spoken; and if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> confesses, that he was in want at that time, he did not say that he was in poverty at that time, (which is the sence that (want) in his charge carries) or in such want, as to be put upon any temptations by it, to take that which did not belong unto him▪ only he was more willing to accept of that which was left for him. But this straining of all things to make the innocent guilty, would set the world on fire, if there were but persons enough of such a spirit.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:154339:23"/>
                     <head>Answer.</head>
                     <p>Though you used not the word (want) yet that it came sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably, because he had borrowed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, is of stronger import then the word (want.) For many will rather want, then borrow to buy Land, or rent which he did about that time. And yet this was your Argument to get him that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which was given to the Churches dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, as <hi>Colonel Venables</hi> certifieth himself. And Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> in a Letter to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154339:24"/> Mrs <hi>Venables,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed it was want that caused him to take it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>And whereas he saith <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> might have told him the reason of his borrowing money, It is true, he might so, if he had known what fire-brands had been so neare, what mischief evill w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>kers would have wrought out of harmlesse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssions; Or if Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> had asked after a reason of his bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing money, he should not have been silent, but have declared the best he knew: but it would not have been that reason, for he understood it not, (as he saith) that it was to buy Land or Rent, nor (indeed) was it. What he bought, was bought before this money was borrowed. But what hath he to do with this matter? Whose Agent is he? Or whose cause doth he plead, that he busieth himself in such interposing? If he should suffer upon such an account, what comfort would he have for suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ring as a busie-body in others matters. As for Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> buying Rent, (for Land he bought not) which he so often mentioneth, as if it were some great transgression, that which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned it, might justifie him in it. His own Land was sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ected
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154339:24"/> to the payment of a yearly Rent, which he attempted to free it from, but could not effect it, without buying more then it; for that which he bought of others Rents was for his own security, because his Land was chargeable with the whole Rent-charge of that place, by which meanes he was lyable to suffer, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made default, as very lately some have done; which was a bondage from which he might honestly desire to deliver himself. And if Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> had known all this, and yet would have withheld his money, lest he should further it, Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> losse would not have been much, for he could have helped himself an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way, and Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> his respect would have been but little, and lesse then might justly (all things considered) have been expected.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Answer.</head>
                     <p>You might as well have told him the reason of his borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money, if you had been faithful in your Office; which was to buy Land or Rent, &amp; the <hi>Colonel</hi> would not, (as himself con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth) have so said.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>Whether <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> speak truth or no, is neither to be left to him, nor to Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> nor to any other to judge of: he hath been upon his Oath before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, and if Col. <hi>Venables</hi> have spoken contrary, he hath contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted himself, as by witnesses before the Commissioners doth also appear. As for his Office, and what most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemes him in it, through Gods grace, he understands it, and needes not his instruction, who would limit it to the poore, (as may be feared) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the light of his own Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And it is notoriously untrue, that he interposed betwixt the poor and the money, when as (1) there was not any mention of the poor at all, and (2) there was never any sum of money given to the <hi>Deacons,</hi> for the use of the Church, but the greater part by far, did still go to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154339:25"/> Teaching-Officers or Officer, and that most righteously as before hath been plentifully shewed. Whereas he saith, Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> reported that he was 800 <hi>l.</hi> better then in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of these troublesom times: it hath been often asserted, but never proved, and Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> doth believe, that it is notoriously false. Nor doth he know how it could be consistent with truth, at such time when he should speak it, if he spoke any thing at all to that purpose.</p>
                  <p>He remembers that he hath some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken occasion, and once in this mans company, to dehort from worldly mindedness, and to a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendance upon God, for outward things from his own experience, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he had found it thus, that when he most sought the world, it most fled from him, and when he most did cast it off, and waited upon God in the work that he had called him unto, he then enjoyed most of it.</p>
                  <p>Why <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> did not give <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> 40. shillings, the reason is in readiness, because Col. <hi>Venables</hi> did not order it to be so done, but left it for Mr. <hi>Eaton.</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Col. <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> hath given wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to this bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re the Church.</note> And why Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> doth not give it him, seeing he knowes now, that it was the Colonels minde for <hi>Ralph</hi> to have it, and not he to have it at all, hath been declared before the Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, <hi>viz.</hi> because Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> himself undertook to provide for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154339:25"/>
                     <hi>Ralph Hall,</hi> and declared he left the whole 10 l▪ for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, viz.</hi> Ba. Bruen, Mr. Fisher, <hi>Mr.</hi> Angier, are witnesses that this was proved by the Oaths of many.</note> and this was done when he was called to give witness of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truth of that matter, (how he had left that money) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church. And there are the Oaths of many godly men, taken for the proving of it.</p>
                  <p>And though Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> did once think that it was by some mistake, that he had it all delivered unto him, and thereupon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to return 40 s. back: yet that was his mistake, for (1) Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Venables</hi> acquitted him from it in private discourse▪ after he had so promised, and afterwards more publiquely before the Church, as hath been shewed already. And if Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> will vary from this, and declare that he intended 40 s. of it for <hi>Ralph Hall,</hi> and thereby endeavour to bring a scandall upon Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> he is like to have the dishonour of it at last, and Mr <hi>Eaton</hi> is not bound to attend him in his varying.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:154339:24"/>
                     <head>Answer.</head>
                     <p>Whether you speak truly or no, in saying he declared no other use for which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it, I shal leave it to <hi>Colonel Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> himselfe, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> saith, he told you, he desired <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> might have <hi>40 s.</hi> out of it, and that you should acquaint the <hi>Church</hi> with it, which had you done, and given <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> the <hi>40.</hi> shillings, had more beseemed a Deacon, whose work is to care for the poor, as <hi>Act. 6.</hi> shews,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154339:25"/> though it would not acquit you from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Instrument on Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> behalf, to interpose betwixt the poor and the money, though he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported he is <hi>800 l.</hi> better then in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of these troublous times.</p>
                     <p>Why did you not give <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> the <hi>40 s.</hi> and why doth not Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> give it him, seeing he knowes now it was the Colonels minde, and not he to have it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all, as Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> hath confessed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and gave <hi>Ralph Hall 10 s.</hi> and wrote to Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> that he would give him the other <hi>30 s.</hi> and yet afterwards wrote by <hi>William Barret</hi> to the Colonel, that if he would have <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> to have the <hi>30 s.</hi> he must pay it himselfe; for he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154339:25"/> would not, and to this day it is not payd.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>If Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> first intended the ten pounds for the Church,<note place="margin">Edw. Tipping Jo. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mby Ja. Johnson Tho. Newton</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> it was that which was never done since the Church was first constituted, though several sums have been given to the Church by several persons of quality, besides Colonel <hi>Venables;</hi> and the lesse is Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> beholding to him, and yet unless Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed himself so, and by a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mention of Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Edw. Tipping Jo. Wharmby <hi>J.</hi> Johnson Tho. Newton.</note> had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded him, it would not have been so done; for that which is given to the Church, if no more be said, is given to the maintenance of the Teaching-Officer, and what can be spared therefrom to the poor. And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154339:26"/> this Col. <hi>Venables</hi> knowes well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and so do all these persons, though they thus perversly appear. And though Col. <hi>Venables</hi> might so intend, yet it cannot be said, that he therein declared to the truth of his Wives Letter, for there is no such thing mentioned in his Wives Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>But if it were his purpose, and he altered his minde, at least so farre as concerns 8 l. of the 10 l. and if he told his Wife so, why then doth she say in her letter to this man, that Mr. <hi>Eaton payd himselfe for his Journey to London; with the Churches money,</hi> when yet as it seemes 8 l. of it was his, by that change of minde, which the Colonel confessed. And doth he declare to the truth of that part of his Wives Letter? And if not, what an untruth is this man guilty of, that thus argues for him?</p>
                  <p>But the Colonel saith, he d d not know that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> borrowed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy Land or Rents. This is mentioned again, as that which (it seemes) sticks much in all their sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks. What if he did not? Yet (1) Ten pounds would go but a little way in buying Land or Rents; Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> will not be much enriched by it. (2) If he did not know, that it was to buy Rents, (for though Land was alwayes named, yet no Land was bought) yet he knew his own duty, which was to help to beare the burthen of the Church, in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154339:26"/> maintaining Officers, and in other things which occasioned charge to the Church, he being one of the principal members for wealth and riches, at least he once knew it, being a member in the first constitution of the Church. (3) It needed not to have been such a grief and trouble to him, that he changed his minde through misapprehension, and left that money for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> which he intended for the Church; for Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was as much damnified in his estate, (as we are informed) by his journey to <hi>London,</hi> which he took in the time of the Colonels deep af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, as that came unto. We are sorry that there is occasion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring our selves in things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t do and will reflect upon the Colonel. This wretched Pamphlet put forth partly in the defence of the Colonel, by these persons, doth put an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity upon us so to do, (which otherwise we should have been far off from, unlesse we should permit the innocent to suffer by our silence.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Answer.</head>
                     <p>For Colonel <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables</hi> Certificate, he hath declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to the truth of his Wives letter, that he first intended the ten pounds for the <hi>Church,</hi> and not for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> when he brought it to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Newton,</hi> and that it was <hi>Thomas Newtons</hi> telling of him, that it came so opportunely, because Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154339:26"/> money, which moved him to change his minde, and say, he was glad it came so opportunely; but saith he did not know that he had borrowed money to buy Land or Rents, and further saith, that at the same time he did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the whole <hi>10 l.</hi> for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> but bad <hi>Thomas New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> acquaint the Church with it, and desired that <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> might have <hi>40s.</hi> out of it. And Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> himselfe in a Letter to Col. <hi>Vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> confessed that he understood him so, and that he had given <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> ten shillings, and would send the Colonel <hi>30 s.</hi> more, to make it up <hi>40 s.</hi> to give <hi>Ralph Hall,</hi> and the reason that he gave the <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate,</hi> was because
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154339:26"/> Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had so promised as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, which if Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had according performed, he had done <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> no wrong, and if <hi>Col. Venables</hi> gave his <hi>Certificate,</hi> not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the whole of the buslness, as since he hath done, nor did declare the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness at some other times, when he was asked of it, it doth not therefore cleare Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Venables,</hi> viz. the Colonel committed an Errour of love, to cover Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> shame, but shewes his ingratitude, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king such returns to Col. <hi>Venables,</hi> as since he hath done.</p>
                     <p>But he saith, that there was 40 s. notwithstanding this change of the Colonels minde, which he bad <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Newton</hi> to acquaint the Church with that <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> might have it, for he did not intend the whole ten pound for Mr. <hi>Eaton.</hi> This <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his Oath against. If this be so, why then did he declare in the Church that he did intend the whole 10 l. for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> yea at that time, when he first left it with <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> It was proved by Oath against him, before the Commissioners.</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154339:27"/>
                     <p>But he further saith, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                        <hi>Eaton</hi> himself in a Letter to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Venables</hi> confesseth, that he understood him so; <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> should have forty shillings out of the ten pound, &amp;c. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Eaton</hi> (indeed) did understand such a thing some weeks after he had received the ten pounds, and offered to return forty shillings back, but he mistook in so understanding, for, as was said before, Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> first to Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> himself (though now he declares otherwise and there were no witnesses, and therefore it must fall) and afterwards to the Church said, that he intended it wholly for Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> when he first left it; and he at the same time, in the hearing of some Brethren he said, he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> another way; but this hath been spoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to before, and before the Commissioners also, yet they lead us (and indeed enforce us) to these needlesse repetitions.</p>
                     <p>But it is further said, that the Certificate which he gave re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting the ten pounds was bottomed upon that promise of Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ning thirty shillings b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck, (<hi>Ralph Hall</hi> having ten shillings already) but this hath not the least colour for it, because long before the Certificate was given, yea, before he was called by the Church to give witness how he had left that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> knew by a Letter that <hi>William Barret</hi> wrote unto him, that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> would not return any such mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney back nor was there cause, for he had released him from it; and in declaring in open Church that he intended it all for him, and would supply <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> another way. And himself ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the reason,<note place="margin">Of this many h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ve taken their oaths before the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> why Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had done <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> no wrong, because he changed his mind at first when he left the money, and intended Mr. <hi>Eat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n</hi> should have it all, which was long before Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> made any promise of returning any thing back.</p>
                     <p>And if there be an error in the Certificate, or in his answer before the Church, when called to testifie the truth, it was not in that he declared not the whole business, bur in declaring that which was false. For to say, that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had done <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> no wrong, because he altered his mind at first, while with <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> upon <hi>Thomas Newtons</hi> words, and left it all for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> which the oaths declare; when yet the true cause, (as is now alledged) why Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had done <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> no wrong was, because Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had promised to return thirty shillings back, having given ten shillings already, this was not a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154339:27"/> meer silencing of something that was truth, but it was an utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that which was an untruth. And to think that Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> would tell a lie for Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> in favour to him, unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and untempted thereunto (for to this day it is not charged upon Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> that ever he opened his lips to intreat him to palliate the business for him) is very unreasonable; but every one may see that the temptation is now strong upon him (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving accused Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> in what he formerly cleared him) to pretend, that what he spake before the Church, and since in his Certificate, was in favour, least he should be judged to be a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious slanderer of Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> against his knowledge.</p>
                     <p>And he saith he hath committed an error of love to cover Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> shame, and yet Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> is not the more clear. But who hath told him so? If Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> his sing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny without proof (especially wherein there is so much contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction) is not to be received against any in a matter of such moment. And this is a worse slander then the former (if he have it from him) that after Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> hath abundantly been cleared out of his own mouth, he should overturn his own testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, in saying, he erred by too much love to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> in stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to cover his shame. And who can believe his declaration now, that considers his testimony and certificates before? And how unreasonable is it to say, that it was an errour of love to cover Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> shame, when as neither Mr. <hi>Venables</hi> himself, nor any one from him, did ever charge Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> with any thing that was shameful about this matter? or of this kind, though there was many times private discourse betwixt them; and though his eares were filled with Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> complaints against his Wife, for scandalizing him in that Letter, she wrote to this man.</p>
                     <p>And after he had given his Certificate Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> came to him (having heard of some dark derogatory expressions that came from him to another, which afterwards came to nothing) and intreated him, that if he could lay any thing to his charge,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> charged him in a Letter with this, and in his answer he denies it not.</note> he would deal truly with him, and speak plainly, and he should take it thankfully, but the Colonel would declare nothing, but was troubled that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> should suspect him. And can any man imagine then, that Mr. <hi>Venables</hi> should so declare in the Church, and so certifie to the world to cover his shame, and never tell him of it?</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:154339:28"/>
                     <p>And at that time, when in discourse with another in his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,<note place="margin">Rob. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingsham.</note> he did attempt by suggestion to disparage Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in some expressions (all which was because Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> would not let the matter rest that respected the scandal that his Wife had brought upon him) yet even then he cleared him in reference to the forty shillings, and signified, that he altered in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s mind whilst with <hi>Thomas Newton,</hi> and left it for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and would provide for <hi>Ralph Hall</hi> another way.</p>
                     <p>But all these things have been before the Commissioners, who have determined Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> to be clear (though this Champion for Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> saith he is not) and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared all these imputations, to be groundless, unjust and scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and have exhorted the Authors and fomenters thereof to humiliation and repentance. Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> as he hath informed us, read this whole Section to two of them, and desired them to declare, whether all these things had not been before them; they answered they had: He wished them to speak, whether they had not cleared him notwithstanding, they answered, it was so; He intreated the favour, that they would certifie so much; they answered, they had done it sufficiently already, and would not be obliged to doe it againe upon the coming forth of every idle Pamphlet.</p>
                     <p>And concerning ungratitude: Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> blesseth God he was never in such a condition as to stand in need of Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> lie to hide his shame: But Colonel <hi>Venables</hi> spake the truth, and the whole truth, both in his testimony and certificate, and no lie: And such a truth as <hi>Thomas Newton</hi> by oath hath given witnesse to. And his temptation lies in going about to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say what he hath said, and in putting such a mask upon them, to obscure the evidence of truth in them.</p>
                     <p>There is a Postscript, which because it is not worthy of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reply, we here forbear to transcribe. Yet in a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way it may receive this answer.</p>
                     <p>The scope of these persons by this Postscript, and the preface to their answer appeares to be their own vindication from such aspersions cast upon them (as they say) in the Certificates, but whether they have by this abusive scurrillous Pamphlet wiped them off, or set the impression deeper upon themselves, time will
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154339:28"/> manifest. Before they were cast out they disturbed our meeting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a long time together, by their boysterous unruly spirits, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the latter end began to slander our teaching Elder, and discerning we would proceed against them, they nominated two persons to have the hearing the one, though he be a person whom we honour, yet because we have had a strong jealousie, that he gave them too much encouragement in their turbulent proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, we thought not meet to be a competent Judge; the other we could have admitted if he had been joyned with others, but they not mentioning any else, and we also bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g jealous, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>st by admitting of unnecessary appeals we should give advantage to restlesse and unquiet spirits to resist the power they are under, and to obstruct all Church proceedings, nothing was done, &amp; they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated us upon it, so far as was possible for them to do, in a solemn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ay breaking off from us as unworthy to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with▪ (So may all offenders do to escape censure) But we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, and concluded upon a day to cast them out, unlesse they submitted and manifested repentance: They came all of them (save one) that day to the meeting place; and when the causes of excommunication were read, they greatly disturbed the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, made a great stir and noyse, wrought great confusion by cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>That's a lie, that's a lie,</hi> often: <hi>And let them go on in their lying:</hi> And this was done in the open Congregation, to the great dishonour of God, and contempt of his Ordinance, and the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the prophaner sort to blaspheme.</p>
                     <p>After this two or three of them went on in scandalizing Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> both by reading papers, and by speaking words at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Assises at <hi>Chester,</hi> which occasioned the printing of the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates, and the Certificates being printed, have occasioned (it seemes) this abusive Pamphlet so full of untruths and slanders. This relation makes it to appear, what their spirit was at first, and hath been all along to this last act.</p>
                     <p>Upon their casting out, they complaining in the Congregation, that we would be our own Judges, we made this offer to referre it, and have followed them with motions ever since, declaring our willingnesse, that godly sound men, of what form soever for discipline, might have the hearing of it, but could not prevail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> if the matter be as they present it in this postscript, they might trust their business in the hand of any godly wise persons equally cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154339:29"/> on both sides: But they are too much in love with this way of calumniating, where proof is not required, but they may speak and print without controule, and while the matter comes not to scanning in a judicial way, they may hope to be be believed as soon as we. They have given it out, what a Volume they have in readiness to print, which will cost an hundred pounds to doe it, if we reply. They cry out against us, that we have not cast out Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> for covetousnesse, and many Scriptures are brought when as they themselves are the first (fo farre as we know) that have scandalized him with it, and yet without any proof. But they have long laboured to kindle a fire amongst us, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide betwixt us and him; and if no course can be found to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle such unruly spirits, which are not only Church disturbers, but Commonwealth disturbers also, we shal not know how to live qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly in our habitations. <hi>The good Lord deliver us and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from such unreasonable persons, and direct us what to do, for it is grievous to us to be forced to answer such spirits, according to their outrage and madness.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="certificate">
            <head>A Copy of a Certificate given under the hands of the Ministers and Messengers of several Congregationall Churches meeting at <hi>Manchester,</hi> shortly after the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the Authors of this Pamphlet. <hi>At which meeting these persons gave their presence, and one of them submitted at the first to be judged by that Assembly, but afterwards declined, and the other two stood out against it.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill 29. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>WE do hereby certifie whom it may concern, that having heard in part the matter of controversie debated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Church meeting at <hi>Stockpont</hi> and some members lately
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154339:29"/> excommunicated Members, a proud and turbulent spirit, and much unchristian carriage, which inclines us to believe (not fully determining till we have had a full hearing of the matter now deferred for a season) that the Church were necessitated to doe what they did, and were regular in their proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them.</p>
            <p>The excommunicate Members, concerning whom we thus cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, are,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Ridgway.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Bruckshaw.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Worrall,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hannah</hi> his Wife.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Ministers of the Gospel.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Moxon</hi> Sen.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Roote.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Michael Briscoe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Iolly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ierem. Marsden.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Messengers of the Churches.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Hodgson.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rand. Sharples.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Washington</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marmad. Reynor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles Boardman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Yates.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Io. Greenwood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Io. Dickson.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Hamond.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Samuel Wardman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Wilson.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Lawson.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:154339:30"/>
            <head>The Particular <hi>Answer</hi> of me WILLIAM BARRET, Unto So much as is inserted by <hi>John Bruckshaw,</hi> &amp; <hi>Robert Ridgway,</hi> concerning me (particularly and expressely by name) in their untrue and malicious Pamphlet intituled <hi>An Answer to the aforesaid Certificates, pretending to clear Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>from two summes of money sent and given by Colonell</hi> Venables <hi>to the Church called</hi> Duckenfield <hi>Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrst, you <hi>John Bruckshaw,</hi> and <hi>Robert Ridgway,</hi> have asserted an untruth, in the latter end of the sixth, and in the beginning of the seventh Page of your said Pamphlet, within the confines of these words, <hi>(viz.) Which relation at the request, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of</hi> William Barret, <hi>one of the Elders, whose hand is at the aforesaid Certificate (to whom she also told it) we gave in writing under our hands to the Church:</hi> For though it be true, that you gave a relation under your hands, of what you pretended <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had told you, yet she never told or gave me such a relation as you gave me under your hands, but peremptorily denyed to your faces, that part of the relation wherein the greatest stresse lay, and that before the Church; her husband also at the same time witnessing with her against you both (as you very well know) Neither is it a truth which you u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>duely affirme in the sixt Page of your said Pamphlet in these words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> William Barret <hi>aforesaid, told</hi> George Downes <hi>one of your members that</hi> Joyce Hall <hi>cleared us:</hi> For (to the utmost of my remembrance) I never told <hi>George Downs</hi> or any one else, that <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had cleared you, although I might say, that I heard that <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had afterwards confessed more tending to clear you then she did when she was before the Church; For to that purpose (to my remembrance) I heard <hi>Katharine Ashton</hi> say.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Page, you aske <hi>William Barret, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>hath cleared himselfe by bringing the money back to the Church, and confessing how evilly he hath carried it, yea, so as it might be knowne so farre as the money was known of; For</hi> (say you) William Barret <hi>told us and some others (being asked what
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154339:30"/> would be done about the money) That he (viz. Mr.</hi> Eaton) <hi>would never be cleared untill he had done so, for he had been with Colonel</hi> Venables <hi>who told him that he sent the money to the Church. And</hi> William Barret <hi>further sayd, that all the world should not make him a penniworth of</hi> Eaton, <hi>and if he were out of the Society, he would not come in againe, if he might have his hat full of gold and silver to come in againe; And this he spake at two severall times, and yet his name is at the Certificate. Now if Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>have not cleared himselfe as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oresaid, who comes nearest to lying, forging, and malicious sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndering?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, First I may truly say, that I do not remember that ever I sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke so much as the substance of what is in this relation, much lesse all the circumstance thereof as they are layd downe. But for further answer thereunto, I shall say this.</p>
            <p>First, I hope Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> hath cleared himselfe from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of unrighteousnesse in the reception of the aforesaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, and that without bringing it back to the Church; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I grant, that if your relation had been true, which you pretended you had from <hi>Joyce Hall;</hi> nay, if so much of it as she gave me, had been right without contradiction, Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> could not have cleared himself without restoring the mony back. And I confess also that I was jealous for some time how it would proove. But when I came to the sight of Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> letter, whose hand writing I very well knew, and also came to understand how the <hi>Deacons</hi> had ordered the moneyes, and heard <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> and you contradict one another before the Church with high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales to heaven, together with severall other passages (which for brevity sake I do here omit) by which I was convinced that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> was cleare from unrighteousnesse in receiving the said moneyes: I durst not then be so implacable and desperately malicious, as to say (as one of you once did of Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the same businesse) <hi>he hath told a long Story, but he is not cleared yet:</hi> but was so farre convinced as to signe a Certificate for Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> his clearing, and so did many others, and Colonel <hi>Venables,</hi> did the same thing himselfe, who was the donor of the said monyes. And I was the rather induced so to do, because I clearely perceived at the last, that your designe was not at all to reforme Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> (in case he had been guilty) but to cast shame and bring disgrace upon him, in which course your late Pamphlet declares you do persist.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:154339:31"/>
            <p>And whereas you alledge, that I further said, <hi>that no man shall make me a penniworth of</hi> Eaton, I answer; That I do neither rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ember nor believe that ever I spake these words to you nor any other person, or that ever I made mention of the meanest mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church (unto which I do relate) in such termes in all my life, in seriousnesse, but I either called them by their proper names, or gave them their du additions; &amp; therefore I was not like to sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ak more scornfully and sleightly of Mr <hi>Eaton</hi> (who was then and is now my Pastor) then ever I did of any other. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I do confesse, that partly by your meanes and for your sakes and some others, my aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions were too much alienated for a time from Mr. <hi>Eato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he and I often fallen into hot contests, in relation to some that were then my dearest Intimates that I had in all the Church, (of which number the one of you were, in whom I hoped there had been more faithfulnesse, and integrity then since I have found in you.) I did therefore stand and appear for you, in what I conceived you either did well, or intended well, and thereby Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and my selfe, did sometimes fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mutual sharp expressions face to face, the inconvenience whereof, I hope the Lord hath made us so sens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble, that no such thing will be for the future. Yet in those dayes, yea, and after the said monies came into question, I did several times, both to you and others, expresse my selfe in such language towards Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> as favoured rather of prejudice, then that tenderness that I ought to have manifested towards him, the which I seriously con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idered of within my selfe, and was so troubled thereat, that long since I did of my own accord, (without being prest there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by any) freely confess at a Church-meeting, that I had mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried therein, and I thought it was a duty incumbent upon me so to do. And I think if you had been so ingenious, as to have done the like, you might have had more true comfort and peace in your souls, then you are like to have, whilest you remain ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, and act the part of Incendiaries, to divide betwixt Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and me, hoping thereby to break the Church, the which if you could effect, one great part of your design were over; in order whereunto, you tell stories at all adventures, being so blinded with malice, that you do not only unfaithfully make that publique, which past from me to you in secret, in the time of our greatest intimacy, but also present things with additions, being
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154339:31"/> no other then the Inventions of your own brains in divers parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>And as to that which immediately followes in the same page, <hi>viz. That if I were not of the Society, I would not come in again, if I might have my Hat full of Gold and Silver to come in again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, Its very true, that when contests were grown very high, betwixt Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and some of my dearest Intimates, and betwixt Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and me also, mostly upon their account, I do believe, that if I had then been free, I should not have joyned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Society, until it had been in a more peaceable posture; And I hope it proceeded not out of disrespect to the Church, but from a desire of living in peace, my spirit not being able to beare those contentions, which were for the most part occasioned by reason that I was through my too much affection, overweened concerning them. For I doubt not, but if the Church it selfe were called thereunto, it would witness how often I have been invited from it, in case I had minded to have left it, before any of the said divisions were ingendred. But that I ever mentioned an Hatt full of Gold and Silver, upon the said accompt, is more then I remember or believe. But suppose I had said all that you charge upon me in this particular, might I not for all that si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne the said Certificate. Nay, suppose my affections had been so ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated from Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> that I could not with freedom have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the Society with him; yet might I not for all that signe a Certificate for his clearing, in relation to such a thing as I was convinced he was clear in? Sure I might, unlesse I were guided by your spirit, for I perceive, that unless one please you, you will not speak the truth for him. But this is apparent, that your malice is so inveterate against Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> that both of you have lent <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yce Hall</hi> a lye against your own solemn appeales to God, because she now takes part with you against him; for you say in your Pamphlet, that she spoke truth for the substance, and if so, it must needes follow, that you both spoke an untruth for the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; for her relation and yours in one of the most subs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>antial things, were as opposite and contrary one to another, as the East is to the West. And if she spoke truth for the substance in that thing wherein she and you contested one against another, with high appeales to God, then what did you lesse then solemnly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare your selves▪ before many witnesses.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:154339:32"/>
            <p>And unto that which you say, p. 13. <hi>And the aforesaid Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Barret saith yet, he did not know of the money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, that <hi>William Barret</hi> may say yet, that he did not know of the money, <hi>viz.</hi> That he did not remember, that he had heard either of the 24 l. much lesse of 26. or 28 l. as it was doubtfully expressed at first, when <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> made the relation concerning it; For what I cannot remember at present, I cannot know at present, and I did not remember that ever I saw Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> Letter relating to it, until Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> came to be questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about it. Yet will it therefore follow, that there was no such Letter, because at first I could not remember that I had seen it? Nay, will it therefore follow, that there was no such Letter, though as yet, I could not remember that I saw it at the first? Or will it therefore follow, that no one else, had either seen the said Letter, nor heard of the monies, because I had not? Or when I saw the Letter since the said monies came into questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, must I except against it, because I could not remember that I had seen it before that time? or when I was convinced, that it was really Mr. <hi>Taylers</hi> Letter, being very well acquainted with his hand-writing, must I say it was forged? Sure such consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would be very strange ones.</p>
            <p>And as to that which followes in the same page, where you say in effect, <hi>That you were forewarned by</hi> William Barret <hi>afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>did not so much matter the business of the mony, so that he could entrap you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, That I do confess I do not well know what you would have the Reader to understand by this; for if you intend that I meant that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> did not so much matter his own vindication, provided he could entrap you. I hope there is not any so unreasonable, as to believe that ever I expressed my selfe in such termes, as would beare such an Interpretation, or at least, I might be thought unreasonable, in case I had so exprest my selfe, the which I never did (to my now remembrance) as you have laid them down. But you have formed them out of your own brain, being so overpowred by a spirit of delusion that when you have some ground, of which you might deduce a truth, you cannot leave it until you have formed it into a lye. And this is the effect and result of a consultation betwixt the Father of untruths, and your own hearts. For though I spake not what you assert,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154339:32"/> yet I spake something of a snare; And to my now remembrance, it was to this purpose, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z.</hi> That I was perswaded that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had rather you were taken in the snare, then <hi>Joyce Hall,</hi> and therefore sore-warned you to look to your selves, and in this I spake as I then believed; and if I were mistaken, I so much wronged Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> (and if so, I am sorry for it,) and I cannot but believe that I was mistaken, because I have lately heard Mr <hi>Eaton</hi> professe so much.</p>
            <p>And as to that in the 14th page, in these words: <hi>But is not William Barret aforesaid, rather a Calumniator, who certifieth thus now, and yet since</hi> Octob. 6. 1656. <hi>came to us, and desired us to appear in the discovery of this money, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to second us therein, and wished us to stay a while, before we break off, that he might go out with us, time would not be so long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answer,</hi> There is much deceit in this relation of yours, especially in the design thereof, for to the utmost of my now remembrance, I never spake the words, as you have here presented them, neither had I such intent in speaking what I did say, as is apparently your designe, to make the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to believe. For though I might say after <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had made a relation to me of Mr. <hi>Eatons</hi> miscarrying, (as she pretended) and also considering what you your selves related, and at last gave it under your hands, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e said <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had told you the whole of it.) I might say, yea, it was my duty to say, that if you would appeare in the discovery of it, I would second you therein. But did I ever promise to assist you in an untruth? For you asserted (as hath been already h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted) more then ever <hi>Joyce Hall</hi> had declared to me, or would confess that she had spoken to you, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denyed the main part thereof to your faces. And therefore if I did say as abovesaid, yet ought I not to certifie the truth on <hi>Mr. Eaton</hi> his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, when before <hi>Octob.</hi> 1657. I was satisfied that <hi>Mr. Eaton</hi> had done no wrong in the reception of the said money? Indeed, if I had encouraged you to appeare in the discovery of the said monies in the year 1657. and yet had signed the said Certificate before in 1656. you might then have cast it in my teeth, to some purpose. But is it any strange thing, that I should come to be fully satisfied in 1657. of that which I doubted of in 1656. Therefore what have you done, but discovered your folly and malice, in this particular which is so great, that I am apt to believe, that if <hi>Mr. Eaton</hi> were at present never so cleare in your own Consciences, yet such is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteracy of your envy against him, that you would not expresly pronounce him clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t whereas you add, that I wished you to stay a while before you broke off, that I might go out with you, time would not be so long.</p>
            <p>I answer, That to the utmost of my remembrance, I never spake the words, as you lay them down, neither do at present remember that ever you or I mentioned breaking off, no not in the time of our gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>test intim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy. Neither do I remember, that I heard of your resolution to break off from the Church, until you together with others, did solemnly declare it in the presence of the Church, when I expected no such thing from you. But you have of la e so accustomed your selves to wander, that you cannot keep the way of truth, but reel and stagger for the most part in all your
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154339:33"/> stories; yet this I do remember, that after their grew some clashings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Church, or betwixt Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and <hi>Robert Ridgway</hi> and his Wife, they two did several times enquire of me, why the Church would not grant them their dismission? I have then answered, that I would not have them to speak of a dimission whilst things were in debate betwixt the Church and them; and once (at the least) I remember I used this as an argument to take them off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om any fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her speech or mention of a dismission (in that juncture of time) that if they would have patience a while, it might be ere long we should go out together; now this was when the intimacie was great betwixt them and me, and some prejudice was generated in my thoughts towards Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> partly upon their account, so as I was tempted to think that I could have more comfort in their fellowship (together with some others, which were then very precious in my eyes) without him, then with him without them. Yet I never entertained any resolution, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at that time, or any other, to break off proposterously, as they and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers afterwards did, but ever disswaded them from it, as they very well know, and must confesse, in case they have not forgotten to speak the truth. But I do now freely acknowledge hereby, that if I had then left Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> and the Church for their fellowship, I had made a very ill bargain for my self, both in relation to persons and things, for though I have known some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Christian intimacy well nigh these thirty yeares last past, yet I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found by such sad experience so much unfaithfulnesse as I have done from the said <hi>Robert Ridgway</hi> and his Wife: For I once thought we might have trusted one another with things of greatest concernment, but because I would not run with them into all their excesses against <hi>Mr. Eaton,</hi> they have maliciously raked up whatever they could bethink themselv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of that passed from me to them in private, and have made use thereof wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h many additions of untruths to divide betwixt him and me The Lord rebuke that Inveteracie of spirit which hath taken hold upon them, and deliver them from it, that they may no longer be over powered by it, but may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the Wise man saith, <hi>Prov,</hi> 11.13. <hi>A tale-bearer revealeth se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, but he that is of a faithful spirit concealeth the matter.</hi> Yea, I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh, that we may all consider, <hi>That a froward mouth soweth strife, and a whisperer se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parateth chief friends, Prov.</hi> 16.28. And the rather let us think of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>a brother offended is harder to be won, than a strong City and their content<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are like the bars of a Castle, Prov.</hi> 18.19. This is found true in these dayes by woful experience, and that is the cause why so few do take that whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some counsel in the 5th of <hi>James</hi> and 16. verse, <hi>Confesse your faults one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed;</hi> but rather run the way that the Prophet complaines of, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. <hi>I heard the def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing of many, &amp;c. report, say they, and we will report it:</hi> And Chap. 18.18. <hi>Come let us smite him with the tongue.</hi> Therefore it concernes the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to believe and pray, That <hi>the God of peace will bruise Satan under their feet shortly,</hi> Rom. 16.20.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>